<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" obkms_id="7212f6b4-ae06-45e6-94b9-a9063ba9775a" obkms_process="TRUE">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PhytoKeys</journal-id>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/PhytoKeys.2.747</article-id>
      <title-group>
        <article-title obkms_id="96fbc85c-b67d-43a9-ac22-17591ad43f5e" obkms_process="TRUE">
                    Nesogordonia tricarpellata (Dombeyaceae), a new species from Madagascar that compels modification of the morphological circumscription of the genus
                </article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple" obkms_id="2cb62488-4310-43ff-bfd7-14230c43d0cc" obkms_process="TRUE">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Skema</surname>
            <given-names>Cynthia</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple" obkms_id="390d43c4-ae07-4faa-9848-e37ce60105ee" obkms_process="TRUE">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Dorr</surname>
            <given-names>Laurence J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1">
        <label>Institute of Molecular BioSciences, Massey University, Private Bag 11222, Palmerston North 4442, New Zealand</label>
      </aff>
      <aff id="A2">
        <label>Department of Botany, MRC-166, National Museum of Natural History, Smithsonian Institution, P.O. Box 37012, Washington, DC 20013-7012 U.S.A.</label>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="corresp">
          <p>Corresponding author: Cynthia Skema (<email xlink:type="simple">C.Skema@massey.ac.nz</email>).</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="edited-by">
          <p>Academic editor: Hanno Schaefer</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>11</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>9</fpage>
      <lpage>15</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Cynthia Skema, Laurence J. Dorr</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract obkms_id="1d4a18db-1cd9-4471-9a8b-a47ec04f7ba4" obkms_process="TRUE">
        <label>Abstract</label>
        <p><tp:taxon-name obkms_id="aecb45a7-3a34-45eb-b10b-080e2067250d" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia tricarpellata</tp:taxon-name> Skema &amp; Dorr, <bold>sp. nov.</bold>, a new species from southeastern Madagascar, is described and illustrated. It differs from all other species of <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="8aa3509d-296d-4425-9b21-7b4e191ff055" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia</tp:taxon-name> Baill. in having 6–9 stamens, 3 staminodes, a 3-carpellate ovary, and a 3-valved capsule. These androecial and gynoecial characters require modification of the long-standing circumscription of the genus. The new species also has the southernmost geographic range of any species in the genus.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group obkms_id="05bc157f-23ad-4aa0-a5e9-922338a89c5c" obkms_process="TRUE">
        <label>Keywords</label>
        <kwd>Anosyenne Mountains</kwd>
        <kwd>conservation</kwd>
        <kwd>Dombeyaceae</kwd>
        <kwd>endemism</kwd>
        <kwd>Madagascar</kwd>
        <kwd>Malvaceae</kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Nesogordonia</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>taxonomy</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="Introduction" obkms_id="e1c4d90d-429e-43d3-978c-d9873770543d" obkms_process="TRUE">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><tp:taxon-name obkms_id="ed0a1983-b500-4453-bb6d-d5d79e33d504" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia</tp:taxon-name> Baill. (<tp:taxon-name obkms_id="f8bb6717-a0a7-4e69-99c3-cffa4f68f00e" obkms_process="TRUE">Dombeyaceae</tp:taxon-name>, or <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="c7e79d2f-bf8d-4b22-bde5-501eb244a4c4" obkms_process="TRUE">Malvaceae</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="37c2d7c7-31ce-4643-887d-0b1e80649d35" obkms_process="TRUE">Dombeyoideae</tp:taxon-name>) is a genus of ca. 20 species of small to large trees (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Arènes 1959</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Barnett 1988</xref>, Dorr and Barnett in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Cheek and Dorr 2007</xref>). Three species occur in tropical Africa and one in the Comoro Islands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Labat et al. 2000</xref>). The majority of species, however, are endemic to Madagascar and as previously unexplored areas of this island are surveyed botanically additional novel<!--PageBreak-->ties are discovered (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Barnett 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Callmander et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Rakotoarivelo et al. 2010</xref>), including the following new species that compels us to modify the long-established morphological circumscription of the genus.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="Systematics">
      <title>Systematics</title>
      <tp:taxon-treatment obkms_id="d3405913-9c50-425b-951b-70f01ded2f1d" obkms_process="TRUE">
        <tp:nomenclature obkms_id="96974b45-6890-4a7f-8cd0-5c16c2cc9eed" obkms_process="TRUE">
          <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="4c0f968a-29c3-449a-82ef-6505ba06d3bf" obkms_process="TRUE">
            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Nesogordonia</tp:taxon-name-part>
            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">tricarpellata</tp:taxon-name-part>
            <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:ipni.org:names:77109527-1</object-id>
          </tp:taxon-name>
          <tp:taxon-authority>Skema &amp; Dorr</tp:taxon-authority>
          <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
          <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>
        </tp:nomenclature>
        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Latin">
          <title>Latin</title>
          <p>Species gynecio 3-carpello et 3 staminodiis a congeneribus differt.</p>
        </tp:treatment-sec>
        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type">
          <title>Type.</title>
          <p><bold>Madagascar:</bold> Toliara: Anosy, Fort-Dauphin, Iabakoho, Antsotso, forêt humide de basse altitude Ivohibe–Bemangidy, près d’un cours d’eau, 24°34'17"S, 047°12'07"E, 90 m. 12 February 2006 (fl). J. Rabenantoandro, F. Randriatafika, B. Mara, P. Lowry, and E. Lowry 1711 (holotype: US!; isotypes: MO!, TAN!).</p>
        </tp:treatment-sec>
        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
          <title>Description.</title>
          <p><italic>Tree</italic>, 4–8 m tall, to 15 cm d.b.h.; young stems glabrous, pale whitish gray to brown with prominent leaf scars; older stems darker brown; terminal bud to 3 mm long, subulate to falcate, strigose. <italic>Leaves</italic> alternate, entire, persistent; petioles 1–1.5 cm long, glabrous or with a few minute, stellate hairs or with a row of simple hairs (Randriamampionona 470), slightly to noticeably pulvinate basally and apically, drying dark brown; blade elliptic to narrowly elliptic, 5–7.5 × 2.5–3 cm, subcoriaceous, dark green above, lighter green below, base obtuse to rounded or attenuate (Randriamampionona 451), margin shallowly crenulate, slightly revolute, apex long acuminate, mucronulate (as an extension of the 1° vein below), glabrous above and below or with mostly simple, erect to appressed hairs restricted to 1° vein above (Randriamampionona 470), venation brochidodromous, 1° vein conspicuously raised below, 2° veins visible but less prominently raised below; domatia ovoid to almost circular tufts of erect or arching simple and stellate hairs in axils of 1° and 2° veins below, 0.6–0.9 × 0.5–0.6 mm; stipules caducous, not seen. <italic>Inflorescences</italic> axillary, paniculate cymes, to 4.5 cm long, (1–) 2–3-flowered; peduncles to 2.6 cm long, glabrous or with a few minute, stellate hairs; pedicels to 1.5 cm long, articulated 3.2–4.3 mm below base of the flower, glabrous or with a few minute, stellate hairs especially above the articulation. <italic>Epicalyx</italic> fugacious, not seen. <italic>Flower</italic> budsglobose, 3–4 × 3–4 mm, sepals valvate, sutures slightly raised. <italic>Calyx</italic> 5-parted, shortly fused at base; <italic>sepals</italic> ovate, 5–5.5 × 1.7–2.2 mm, fleshy, heterotrichous outside with shorter-armed (ca. 0.02 mm long) stellate hairs beneath sparsely distributed longer-armed (ca. 0.2 mm long) stellate hairs, sparingly pubescent inside with few stellate hairs mostly near the sutures, both surfaces with a denser patch of minute stellate or simple hairs apically. <italic>Petals</italic> 5, ovate to elliptic, 3.5–4 × 2–2.5 mm, weakly asymmetric, slightly constricted apically, fleshy, glabrous, white. <italic>Androecium</italic> biseriate, outer whorl of 3 fascicles of 2–3 stamens each (6–9 stamens total), shortly (to 0.5 mm) fused basally, inner whorl of 3 staminodes; stamens<!--PageBreak--> laminar; anthers 2.7–2.8 × 0.8–1.1 mm; lanceolate to oblong, asymmetric, 2.8–2.9 × 0.8 mm, apex acute to acuminate, fleshy. <italic>Gynoecium</italic> superior, ca. 1.5 × 1.5 mm, 3-carpellate, densely covered by small lepidote scales (ca. 0.15 mm in diameter); ovules 2 per carpel, basally winged, placentation subapical, axile; styles 3, connate, 2–2.5 mm <!--PageBreak-->long; stigma lobes 3, ca. 0.8 mm long, fleshy, stigmatic surface on interior apical portion of lobes, deep red drying black. <italic>Capsules</italic> woody, obconic, 1.5–2 × 1.2–1.5 cm, slightly verrucose with scattered scales or short-armed stellate hairs, chestnut brown, apex depressed with a central umbo, rim not present or scarcely developed. <italic>Seeds</italic> 4–5 × 3–4 mm, seed wings 5–10 × 4–5 mm.</p>
          <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait" obkms_id="56ad40ec-3556-468d-9e1b-7ffc31ace924" obkms_process="TRUE">
            <label>Figure 1.</label>
            <caption>
              <p><tp:taxon-name obkms_id="4df7b76b-c393-4285-8053-cc5b0e0aeadd" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia tricarpellata</tp:taxon-name> Skema &amp; Dorr. <bold>A</bold> habit <bold>B</bold> leaf blade below <bold>C</bold> leaf blade below, showing detail of domatia <bold>D</bold> flower <bold>E</bold> flower, calyx and corolla removed to show stamens, staminodes, ovary, stigma, and style <bold>F</bold> anther (right) and staminode (left) <bold>G</bold> gynoecium with lepidote scales on ovary and 3-parted style <bold>H</bold> detail of lepidote scales <bold>I</bold> immature fruit, longitudinal section showing position of winged ovule. Line drawing by L.R. Andriamiarisoa from herbarium specimen; voucher Rabenantoandro et al. 1711 (MO).</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="export.php_files/PhytoKeys-002-009-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
          </fig>
        </tp:treatment-sec>
        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution" obkms_id="0202df56-1fc1-46f0-bcaf-a3c34c6ad90a" obkms_process="TRUE">
          <title>Distribution.</title>
          <p>Endemic to southeastern Madagascar, where it is known from two collections made in Parcelle 1 of the Parc National d’Andohahela (formerly Réserve Naturelle Intégrale d’Andohahela) and one on the lower slopes of the Ivohibe–Bemangidy forest (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>).</p>
          <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait" obkms_id="ab5bdfef-279b-438b-ad54-f750d03df463" obkms_process="TRUE">
            <label>Figure 2.</label>
            <caption>
              <p>Map of extreme southeastern Madagascar showing where <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="0f224f93-0cb9-4e24-b92c-593ba5cbf6fd" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia tricarpellata</tp:taxon-name> Skema &amp; Dorr has been collected and these two localities in relation to the three parcels that comprise the Parc National d’Andohahela.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="export.php_files/PhytoKeys-002-009-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
          </fig>
        </tp:treatment-sec>
        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Ecology">
          <title>Ecology.</title>
          <p>Evidently restricted to humid forest from 90–500 m. Flowering specimens were collected in February (floral buds) and June (mature flowers). A fruiting specimen was collected in June.</p>
        </tp:treatment-sec>
        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
          <title>Etymology.</title>
          <p> The epithet was chosen to highlight the fact that the gynoecium of this species is 3-carpellate.</p>
        </tp:treatment-sec>
        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Conservation status">
          <title>Conservation status.</title>
          <p> At present, this species is known from three collections and two localities, only one of which is protected (Parc National d’Andohahela). Based on this and estimates of an extent of occurence &lt; 100 km2 and an area of occupancy &lt; 10 km2, <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="45f68d5d-6f08-4cae-9e5c-1dfb3a175137" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia tricarpellata</tp:taxon-name> is assigned a preliminary status of Critically Endangered (CR B1ab(i-iv) + B2ab(i-iv)) following the criteria and categories of the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">IUCN (2001)</xref>.</p>
        </tp:treatment-sec>
        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Specimens examined">
          <title>Specimens examined.</title>
          <p><bold>Madagascar:</bold> Toliara: Intégrale Réserve # 11, Andohahela, Parcelle 1, Isaka Ivondro, 24°40'S, 46°52'E, 100–150 m. 12–23 June 1993 (fl), Randriamampionona 451 (MO), Ibid., 12–23 June 1993 (fr), Randriamampionona 470 (MO).</p>
        </tp:treatment-sec>
        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Discussion">
          <title>Discussion.</title>
          <p> We have no doubt that this new speciesbelongs in <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="800a68cd-4086-431d-9a33-a84ef29512f9" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia</tp:taxon-name> asit has the fruit and seeds unique to the genus: an obovoid woody capsule containing seeds with long, basal wings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1I</xref>). <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="20e97068-5b8e-401e-9e80-250037eeef07" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia tricarpellata</tp:taxon-name> is remarkable in having an androecium comprised of 6–9 stamens in an outer whorl and 3 staminodes in an inner whorl; a 3-carpellate ovary; 3 style branches and 3 stigma lobes; and a 3-valved capsule (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1E, G</xref>). While the number of stamens is variable in other species of <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="19cc43ed-5f47-4f85-aaac-edb67407f286" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia</tp:taxon-name>, the outer whorl typically possesses some multiple of five (usually 10–25 total) stamens and the inner whorl possesses either 5 free staminodes (most species) or 5 stamens (<tp:taxon-name obkms_id="bfde4f4e-e7b6-4daf-bdf3-489882c89fec" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia abrahamii</tp:taxon-name> L.C. Barnett, <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="f2eb752f-254c-4895-af22-8bd7c7d0a513" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia ambalabeensis</tp:taxon-name> Arènes, and <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="42e169bd-1ae1-4d0e-90a1-3904766651ce" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia fertilis</tp:taxon-name> H. Perrier). All other species of <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="d19c46f4-2df3-4f4e-b2db-d8982932e10a" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia</tp:taxon-name> have 5-carpellate ovaries, 5 style branches, 5 stigma lobes, and 5-valved capsules. Although the parts of the androecium and gynoecium of <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="7b85c175-5920-41d7-bad9-48550901a07e" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia tricarpellata</tp:taxon-name> are reduced in number, the flowers of the new species are 5-merous with 5 calyx lobes and 5 petals, which also is characteristic of all other species of <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="3b2fbe32-80b1-4a5e-89e0-e30ab58aacdd" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D</xref>).</p>
          <p>Carpel number is variable in the <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="a48f228b-e36d-4598-8d6b-0fba6860cb27" obkms_process="TRUE">Dombeyaceae</tp:taxon-name>, and it even varies within a genus (8 of 19 genera; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Bayer and Kubitzki 2003</xref>). It is not surprising therefore that carpel number in <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="7714a791-b728-4dec-a32e-d00ba680f6b5" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia</tp:taxon-name> also is variable and the generic description should be modified to accommodate taxa that are 3-carpellate. Among the Malagasy genera of <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="9f3c0b57-d4cb-491d-849d-234e3fb4e0bd" obkms_process="TRUE">Dombeyaceae</tp:taxon-name>, only <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="f6bf37c8-1c67-414b-b070-6251f74c5cf7" obkms_process="TRUE">Dombeya</tp:taxon-name> Cav. (2-, 3-, or 5-carpellate) and <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="64744f68-6d72-442f-a8df-065497399789" obkms_process="TRUE">Helmiopsis</tp:taxon-name> H. Perrier (3- or 5-carpellate) also<!--PageBreak--> have species that are 3-carpellate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Arènes 1959</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Skema and Dorr 2010</xref>). Like <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="862dd824-55f7-4ec1-b0c7-e6ac622c3ab7" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia tricarpellata</tp:taxon-name>, these other 3-carpellate species also possess a pentamerous perianth.</p>
          <p><tp:taxon-name obkms_id="42fdb75c-8084-463e-8a65-8794c870ad36" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia tricarpellata</tp:taxon-name> is the only species in the genus with lepidote scales on the ovary (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1H, I</xref>). All other species of <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="cd14bd05-a041-4b41-91f6-f04ce43bbb0f" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia</tp:taxon-name> have stellate hairs on the ovary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Barnett 1988</xref>). As has been noted before (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Jenny et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Dorr 2001</xref>), a number of other genera in the <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="6791864a-6d42-4f38-be73-ece95d78b4ba" obkms_process="TRUE">Dombeyaceae</tp:taxon-name> have species with either stellate hairs or lepidote scales on the ovary, including <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="24372f69-ab68-4050-87b5-796a4958ad4a" obkms_process="TRUE">Dombeya</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="6d146f79-0feb-43b1-b5f8-68737399e6ae" obkms_process="TRUE">Harmsia</tp:taxon-name> K. Schum., and <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="4da5ab84-24f4-45ad-9b5e-f4b254f783ba" obkms_process="TRUE">Helmiopsis</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
          <p><tp:taxon-name obkms_id="4129d150-d738-480e-ba6a-414051d03d1d" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia tricarpellata</tp:taxon-name> most closely resembles <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="7f436654-c1db-4af6-97f9-fc81e07dc92a" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia micrantha</tp:taxon-name> Arènes. The two species have similar leaf shape, size, and vestiture; inflorescence morphology; and floral bud shape. The leaf blades of both species are glabrous to sparingly pubescent with domatia of tufted hairs in the axils of the 1° and 2° veins below. The leaves of <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="bc346c1e-aec0-4394-9e05-c13dc26c8fad" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia micrantha</tp:taxon-name>, however, are elliptic to obovate (versus elliptic to narrowly elliptic), 2.2–5 × 1.1–2.8 cm (versus 5–7.5 × 2.5–3 cm), apically acute (versus long acuminate), and the margin is undulate to slightly crenulate (versus slightly crenulate). Both species have <!--PageBreak-->(1–) 2–3-flowered axillary, paniculate cymes and globose floral buds. The floral buds of <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="5b6e429c-83f9-41d7-b214-f18706387e3f" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia micrantha</tp:taxon-name>, however, are densely (versus sparingly) stellate pubescent. In addition, the two species have non-overlapping geographical ranges; <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="50ec15f9-e085-480e-a21c-e2ff1963e6e1" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia tricarpellata</tp:taxon-name> appears to be restricted to the Anosyenne Mountains in southeastern Madagascar while <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="ecd40a72-ad64-4e5f-9ed9-1b1c401356ac" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia micrantha</tp:taxon-name> is known only from western Madagascar having been collected principally in the Forêt d’Antsingy.</p>
          <p>The geographical distribution of <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="bc395199-730a-4e4e-a93d-045a48d7a0ae" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia tricarpellata</tp:taxon-name> also is remarkable as the species has the southernmost distribution of any species in the genus. <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="606bc0a4-245c-4c0a-966c-e73aec1ddcef" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia tricarpellata</tp:taxon-name> appears to be restricted to humid forest on the eastern slopes of the Anosyenne Mountains in extreme southeastern Madagascar south of the Tropic of Capricorn (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). The Parc National d’Andohahela includes the southernmost moist “tropical” forest in Madagascar, a forest that appears to be an extension of the humid montane forest common to the north but found at lower elevations in the Anosyenne Mountains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Goodman 1999</xref>).</p>
          <p>Sequence data for one nuclear ribosomal (ITS) and five noncoding plastid markers have been gathered for <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="4ce51529-3f55-4072-9798-dff0a27d3b99" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia tricarpellata</tp:taxon-name> as part of an ongoing phylogenetic study of <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="d8d3fd21-9133-4693-a6ff-ebcf70cde061" obkms_process="TRUE">Dombeyaceae</tp:taxon-name>(Skema in prep.). Parsimony analysis of these data group this new species with <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="e85f9504-d4ed-4ec0-8151-bf3862337fcd" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia humbertii</tp:taxon-name> Capuron (Randrianaivo et al. 1391), the only other species of <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="11324331-a6cb-4a06-bbd8-3f68a1bbbf7f" obkms_process="TRUE">Nesogordonia</tp:taxon-name> sampled, with high support (bootstrap = 100% from 10,000 replicates).</p>
        </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We thank Lala Roger Andriamiarisoa for illustrating this new species, Rose Gulledge for labeling and preparing the plates for publication, Alice <tp:taxon-name obkms_id="22f1e8b6-fb87-40dd-aa44-b10fb370267b" obkms_process="TRUE">Tangerini</tp:taxon-name> for making the map, and Martin Cheek and one anonymous reviewer for helpful comments. The research of C. Skema was supported by NSF Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grant DEB-0709969.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Arènes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1959</year>)<article-title> Sterculiacées</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Humbert</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>) <source>Flore de Madagascar et des Comores</source> <volume>131</volume>. <publisher-name>Firmin-Didot et Cie</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>)<article-title> Two new species of <italic>Nesogordonia</italic> (Sterculiaceae) from Madagascar. Bulletin du Muséum National d’Histoire Naturelle, sect. B</article-title>, <source> Adansonia</source> <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>95</fpage>-<lpage>100</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>)<source> Systematics of <italic>Nesogordonia</italic> Baillon (Sterculiaceae). PhD Thesis</source>, <publisher-name>University of Texas</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Austin</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kubitzki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Malvaceae</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kubitzki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>The families and genera of vascular plants</source> <volume>5</volume>, <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>, <fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>311</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <!--PageBreak-->
      <ref id="B5">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Callmander</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rakotovao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Razafitsalama</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillipson</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buerki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong-Wa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rakotoarivelo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andriambololonera</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koopman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deroin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andriamandranto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Solo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Labat</surname><given-names>J-N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lowry PP</surname><given-names>II</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> New species from two unknown and highly threatened mountainous areas in north-western Madagascar: the Galoka and Kalabenono massifs.</article-title> <source>Candollea</source> <volume>64</volume>:<fpage>179</fpage>-<lpage>202</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dorr</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Sterculiaceae</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Beentje</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghazanfar</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Flora of Tropical East Africa</source>. <publisher-name>Royal Botanic Gardens</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Kew</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dorr</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> A new combination in the endemic Malagasy genus <italic>Helmiopsis</italic> (Malvaceae-Dombeyoideae). Adansonia, sér.</article-title> <source>3,</source> <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>151</fpage>-<lpage>153</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>) (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> A floral and faunal inventory of the Réserve Naturelle Intégrale d’Andohahela, Madagascar: with reference to elevational variation</article-title>. <source>Fieldiana Zoology, ser. 2</source>, <volume>94</volume>: i–viii, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>297</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>IUCN</surname></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<source> IUCN Red List categories and criteria (version 3.1)</source>. <publisher-name>IUCN</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Gland, Switzerland</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jenny</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dorr</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title><italic>Aethiocarpa</italic> reduced to <italic>Harmsia</italic> (Malvaceae, Dombeyoideae).</article-title> <source>Taxon</source> <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Labat</surname><given-names>J-N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munzinger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pascal</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Une nouvelle espèce du genre <italic>Nesogordonia</italic> Baill. (Sterculiaceae) de Mayotte, Archipel des Comores.</article-title> <source>Candollea</source> <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>277</fpage>-<lpage>280</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rakotoarivelo</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Callmander</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andriambololonera</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillipson</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Les espèces endémiques malgaches du genre <italic>Nesogordonia</italic> (Malvaceae)</article-title>. <source>Scripta Botanica Belgica</source> <volume>46</volume>: <lpage>387</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Skema</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dorr</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title><italic>Dombeya gautieri</italic> (Dombeyaceae), a remarkable new species from Madagascar.</article-title> <source>Kew Bulletin</source> <volume>65</volume>:<fpage>305</fpage>-<lpage>310</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
