<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "../../nlm/tax-treatment-NS0.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en" obkms_id="ca172df1-c9f8-4c0b-bc5a-dcff3682f33a" obkms_process="TRUE">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PhytoKeys</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title xml:lang="en">PhytoKeys</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">PhytoKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1314-2011</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1314-2003</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/phytokeys.88.14607</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Data Paper</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title obkms_id="731a0d52-5623-4faa-91b3-062281a81d9c" obkms_process="TRUE">Data Release: DNA barcodes of plant species collected for the Global Genome Initiative for Gardens Program, National Museum of Natural History, Smithsonian Institution</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple" obkms_id="9a5aa7f9-25ce-4501-ab8c-f0e860c89194" obkms_process="TRUE">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Zúñiga</surname>
            <given-names>Jose D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple" obkms_id="62bead23-024c-4148-b41d-21a52e1ad24d" obkms_process="TRUE">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Gostel</surname>
            <given-names>Morgan R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple" obkms_id="04aa11b0-d3ba-41c3-b6c7-1e50066e2b5f" obkms_process="TRUE">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Mulcahy</surname>
            <given-names>Daniel G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple" obkms_id="9ff9adc4-0c63-43c1-91e4-edb05fac9be8" obkms_process="TRUE">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Barker</surname>
            <given-names>Katharine</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple" obkms_id="44b01eb1-18f1-459b-a9fc-0f015548e438" obkms_process="TRUE">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Asia Hill</surname>
            <given-names/>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple" obkms_id="21845698-d6ba-4248-b151-d57bf18bffe3" obkms_process="TRUE">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Sedaghatpour</surname>
            <given-names>Maryam</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple" obkms_id="4f51c094-4799-4bc4-81b9-f8110c1122fa" obkms_process="TRUE">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Vo</surname>
            <given-names>Samantha Q.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple" obkms_id="685315dd-342b-47c1-a705-1fd3cbee10a7" obkms_process="TRUE">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Funk</surname>
            <given-names>Vicki A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple" obkms_id="4f1bf813-8a58-4f57-8394-a4e83d76911f" obkms_process="TRUE">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Coddington</surname>
            <given-names>Jonathan A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Global Genome Initiative, MRC-106, National Museum of Natural History, Smithsonian Institution, P.O. Box 37012 Washington, DC 20013-7012 U.S.A.</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="A2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Botany, MRC-166, National Museum of Natural History, Smithsonian Institution, P.O. Box 37012 Washington, DC 20013-7012 U.S.A.</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="A3">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line>College of Education, North Carolina A&amp;T University, 1601 East Market Street, Greensboro, N.C. 27411 U.S.A.</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="A4">
        <label>4</label>
        <addr-line>University Herbarium and Department of Integrative Biology, University of California, 1001 Valley Life Sciences Building #2465, Berkeley, CA 94720 U.S.A.</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="A5">
        <label>5</label>
        <addr-line>Environmental Science and Policy, George Mason University, 4400 University Drive, Fairfax, VA 22030 U.S.A.</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="corresp">
          <p>Corresponding author: Jose D. Zúñiga (<email xlink:type="simple">zunigaj@si.edu</email>)</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="edited-by">
          <p>Academic editor: Y. Mutafchiev</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>12</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <issue>88</issue>
      <fpage>119</fpage>
      <lpage>122</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2017</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2017</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Jose D. Zúñiga, Morgan R. Gostel, Daniel G. Mulcahy, Katharine Barker, Asia Hill, Maryam Sedaghatpour, Samantha Q. Vo, Vicki A. Funk, Jonathan A. Coddington</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0" xlink:type="simple">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY 4.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract obkms_id="1ccb37f5-bf2b-4084-9a61-632f9460cb52" obkms_process="TRUE">
        <label>Abstract</label>
        <p>The Global Genome Initiative has sequenced and released 1961 DNA barcodes for genetic samples obtained as part of the Global Genome Initiative for Gardens Program. The dataset includes barcodes for 29 plant families and 309 genera that did not have sequences flagged as barcodes in GenBank and sequences from officially recognized barcoding genetic markers meet the data standard of the Consortium for the Barcode of Life. The genetic samples were deposited in the <named-content xlink:type="simple" content-type="institution" xlink:href="http://grbio.org/institution/smithsonian-institution">Smithsonian Institution</named-content>’s <named-content xlink:type="simple" content-type="institution" xlink:href="http://grbio.org/institution/national-museum">National Museum of Natural History</named-content> Biorepository and their records were made public through the Global Genome Biodiversity Network’s portal. The DNA barcodes are now available on GenBank.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group obkms_id="80ac3730-aac9-47fb-8eae-14941ee932a4" obkms_process="TRUE">
        <label>Keywords</label>
        <kwd>DNA barcoding</kwd>
        <kwd>GenBank</kwd>
        <!--PageBreak-->
        <kwd>land plants</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
    <notes>
      <sec sec-type="Citation" id="SECID0ECG">
        <title>Citation</title>
        <p>Zúñiga JD, Gostel MR, Mulcahy DG, Barker K, Hill A, Sedaghatpour M, Vo SQ, Funk VA, Coddington JA (2017) Data Release: DNA barcodes of plant species collected for the Global Genome Initiative for Gardens Program, National Museum of Natural History, Smithsonian Institution. PhytoKeys 88: 119–122. <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3897/phytokeys.88.14607">https://doi.org/10.3897/phytokeys.88.14607</ext-link></p>
      </sec>
    </notes>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="Introduction" id="SECID0ENG" obkms_id="163c0493-1c36-46ff-873d-09328116c734" obkms_process="TRUE">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The Global Genome Initiative (<abbrev content-type="institution" xlink:title="Global Genome Initiative" id="ABBRID0ETG">GGI</abbrev>) is a <named-content xlink:type="simple" content-type="institution" xlink:href="http://grbio.org/institution/smithsonian-institution">Smithsonian Institution</named-content> program to collect, organize, share, and study genomic samples of non-human species. The mission of <abbrev content-type="institution" xlink:title="Global Genome Initiative" id="ABBRID0EYG">GGI</abbrev> is to preserve and understand Earth’s genomic biodiversity. In pursuit of this mission, <abbrev content-type="institution" xlink:title="Global Genome Initiative" id="ABBRID0E4G">GGI</abbrev> aims to collect and preserve genome-quality tissue samples from all major lineages of life on Earth; foster biodiversity genomics research by generating DNA barcodes for dark taxa (i.e., those with no genetic data in online repositories); and promote the use of new technologies to study genomics across the tree of life. <abbrev content-type="institution" xlink:title="Global Genome Initiative" id="ABBRID0ECH">GGI</abbrev> supports the Global Genome Biodiversity Network (<abbrev content-type="institution" xlink:title="Global Genome Biodiversity Network" id="ABBRID0EHH">GGBN</abbrev>), an international network of institutions interested in the preservation of non-human genomic samples (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Seberg et al. 2016</xref>). Members of <abbrev content-type="institution" xlink:title="Global Genome Biodiversity Network" id="ABBRID0EQH">GGBN</abbrev> can make their DNA and tissue collections discoverable on <abbrev content-type="institution" xlink:title="Global Genome Biodiversity Network" id="ABBRID0EVH">GGBN</abbrev>’s data portal (<ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ggbn.org/ggbn_portal/">http://www.ggbn.org/ggbn_portal/</ext-link>), ensuring transparent access and visibility to the genetic resources to the research community.</p>
      <p>The Global Genome Initiative for Gardens Program (<abbrev xlink:title="Global Genome Initiative for Gardens Program" id="ABBRID0ECAAC">GGI-Gardens</abbrev>) is a <abbrev content-type="institution" xlink:title="Global Genome Initiative" id="ABBRID0EGAAC">GGI</abbrev>-funded effort to collect and preserve genetic material from the plant Tree of Life that is not yet represented in any of <abbrev content-type="institution" xlink:title="Global Genome Biodiversity Network" id="ABBRID0ELAAC">GGBN</abbrev>’s partner institutions, and that are currently found in living collections around the globe. In its first phase, the program targeted living plant collections in the Washington, DC area and collected more than 1,800 genome-quality tissues from 209 families, 1007 genera and 1631 species. Moving forward, <abbrev xlink:title="Global Genome Initiative for Gardens Program" id="ABBRID0EQAAC">GGI-Gardens</abbrev> is focused on expanding its partnerships internationally to continue sample and preserve genomic biodiversity from all families and genera, and, potentially, species of plants on Earth.</p>
      <p>The genetic samples collected to date have been deposited in the <named-content xlink:type="simple" content-type="institution" xlink:href="http://grbio.org/institution/smithsonian-institution">Smithsonian Institution</named-content>’s <named-content xlink:type="simple" content-type="institution" xlink:href="http://grbio.org/institution/national-museum">National Museum of Natural History</named-content> Biorepository (<ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://naturalhistory.si.edu/rc/biorepository">http://naturalhistory.si.edu/rc/biorepository</ext-link>) and are available upon request to researchers across the globe (regulations on sampling leaf material can be found here). All corresponding specimen vouchers have been accessioned in the United States National Herbarium (US) or other recognized, partner herbaria. The <abbrev xlink:title="Global Genome Initiative for Gardens Program" id="ABBRID0E2AAC">GGI-Gardens</abbrev> protocol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Gostel et al. 2016</xref>) and US National Herbarium best practices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Funk et al. 2017</xref>) have been published to facilitate the establishment of voucher programs at partner institutions.</p>
      <p><abbrev content-type="institution" xlink:title="Global Genome Initiative" id="ABBRID0EJBAC">GGI</abbrev>’s barcoding strategy data-mines GenBank to detect taxonomic groups that do not have sequences flagged as barcodes, thus allowing <abbrev content-type="institution" xlink:title="Global Genome Initiative" id="ABBRID0EOBAC">GGI</abbrev> to focus sequencing efforts on lineages that are not represented in this repository. Using this method, <abbrev content-type="institution" xlink:title="Global Genome Initiative" id="ABBRID0ETBAC">GGI</abbrev> selected more than 500 plant genera from <abbrev xlink:title="Global Genome Initiative for Gardens Program" id="ABBRID0EYBAC">GGI-Gardens</abbrev> collections and generated sequences for four genetic markers according to the DNA barcode data standard (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Consortium for the Barcode of Life 2005</xref>). As a result, all sequences from officially accepted barcoding regions (two of the four markers targeted, see below) have been labeled with the keyword “BARCODE” in GenBank. All samples were determined at least to genus by the time of publication of this release paper by staff at the living collection where they were collected. Our intentions are to make these data publicly available, to contribute to the DNA Barcode library to assist further research, and to make the presence of <!--PageBreak-->these genomic-quality tissues known and available for the academic community for genomic research and education purposes via a documented application process. All DNA barcode sequences were submitted to GenBank as part of the <abbrev xlink:title="Global Genome Initiative for Gardens Program" id="ABBRID0ECCAC">GGI-Gardens</abbrev> BioProject (ID: PRJNA389125), which is included in Global Genome Initiative’s DNA Barcoding umbrella BioProject (ID: PRJNA384793).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="Data resources and contents of the dataset" id="SECID0EGCAC">
      <title>Data resources and contents of the dataset</title>
      <p>Data are deposited in GenBank under accession numbers <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="MF348326" xlink:type="simple">MF348326</ext-link>-<ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="MF350286" xlink:type="simple">MF350286</ext-link> (see supplementary file 1 for the full list of accession numbers). A total of 1961 sequences have been submitted to GenBank representing 160 families and 521 plant genera, including 29 families and 309 genera that previously did not have sequences flagged as barcodes in this data repository. Two of the four genetic markers sequenced, <italic>rbcL</italic> and <italic>matK</italic>, have been officially recognized as barcoding regions for land plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">CBOL Plant Working Group 2009</xref>). The other two loci targeted in this study, the nuclear ribosomal internal transcribed spacer (nrITS) and the plastid <italic>psbA-trnH</italic> intergenic spacer, are commonly used for barcoding in angiosperms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Kress et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Kress and Erickson 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Hollingsworth et al. 2016</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>All laboratory procedures and computer work were conducted in the Laboratories for Analytical Biology facilities at the <named-content xlink:type="simple" content-type="institution" xlink:href="http://grbio.org/institution/national-museum">National Museum of Natural History</named-content> in Washington, DC and at the Museum Support Center in Suitland, MD. The authors wish to thank Natalia Agudelo and Gabriel Johnson for their continuous support in the lab, Kathryn Faulconer, Sarah Gabler, Kadiera Ingram, Carol Kelloff, Monica Marcelli, Jacob Suissa and Kristen Van Nest for their participation in the collection and curation of the genetic samples and the associated voucher specimens, and Niamh Redmond and Michael Trizna for their advice on post-sequencing data management. This material is based upon work supported by the Global Genome Initiative and <named-content xlink:type="simple" content-type="institution" xlink:href="http://grbio.org/institution/smithsonian-institution">Smithsonian Institution</named-content> Barcoding Network. Any paper(s) resulting directly from this specimen-processing project should reference support from the <named-content xlink:type="simple" content-type="institution" xlink:href="http://grbio.org/institution/smithsonian-institution">Smithsonian Institution</named-content>’s DNA Barcode Network and the Laboratories of Analytical Biology, <named-content xlink:type="simple" content-type="institution" xlink:href="http://grbio.org/institution/national-museum">National Museum of Natural History</named-content>, <named-content xlink:type="simple" content-type="institution" xlink:href="http://grbio.org/institution/smithsonian-institution">Smithsonian Institution</named-content>.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><institution xlink:type="simple">Consortium for the Barcode of Life</institution> (<year>2005</year>) Data Standards for BARCODE Records in INSDC (BRIs). <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.barcodeoflife.org/sites/default/files/DWG_data_standards-Final.pdf">http://www.barcodeoflife.org/sites/default/files/DWG_data_standards-Final.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <!--PageBreak-->
      <ref id="B2">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><institution xlink:type="simple">CBOL Plant Working Group</institution> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A DNA barcode for land plants.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>106</volume>(<issue>31</issue>): <fpage>12794</fpage>–<lpage>12797</lpage>. <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1073/pnas.0905845106">https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0905845106</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Funk</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gostel</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Devine</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelloff</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wurdack</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuccinardi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Radosavljevic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coddington</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) Guidelines for collecting vouchers and tissues intended for genomic work (Smithsonian Institution): Botany best practices. Biodiversity Data Journal 5: e11625. <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3897/BDJ.5.e11625">https://doi.org/10.3897/BDJ.5.e11625</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gostel</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelloff</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wallick</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Funk</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) A workflow to preserve genome-quality tissue samples from plants in botanical gardens and arboreta. Applications in Plant Sciences 4: 1600039. <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3732/apps.1600039">https://doi.org/10.3732/apps.1600039</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kress</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wurdack</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmer</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weigt</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janzen</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Use of DNA barcodes to identify flowering plants.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>102</volume>(<issue>23</issue>): <fpage>8369</fpage>–<lpage>8374</lpage>. <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1073/pnas.0503123102">https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0503123102</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kress</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erickson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) A two-locus global DNA barcode for land plants: The coding <italic>rbcL</italic> gene complements the non-coding <italic>trnH-psbA</italic> spacer region. PLoS ONE. <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pone.0000508">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0000508</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hollingsworth</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van der Bank</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Twyford</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) Telling plant species apart with DNA: form barcodes to genomes. Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B 371: 20150338. <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1098/rstb.2015.0338">https://doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2015.0338</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Seberg</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Droege</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coddington</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Funk</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gostel</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Global Genome Biodiversity Network: saving a blueprint of the Tree of Life–a botanical perspective.</article-title> <source>Annals of Botany</source> <volume>118</volume>: <fpage>393</fpage>–<lpage>399</lpage>. <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1093/aob/mcw121">https://doi.org/10.1093/aob/mcw121</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
      <title>Supplementary materials</title>
      <supplementary-material id="S1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Supplementary material 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>List of samples collected for the Global Genome Initiative for Gardens project selected for DNA barcoding, with GenBank accession numbers and genetic sample identification numbers. All the sequences are included in the <abbrev xlink:title="Global Genome Initiative for Gardens Program" id="ABBRID0EDMAC">GGI-Gardens</abbrev> BioProject.</p>
        </caption>
        <p>Data type: Microsoft Word Document (.docx)</p>
        <p>Explanation note: List of samples collected for the Global Genome Initiative for Gardens project selected for DNA barcoding, with GenBank accession numbers and genetic sample identification numbers.</p>
        <media xlink:href="phytokeys-88-119-s001.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="oo_161051.doc"/>
        <permissions>
          <license xlink:type="simple">
            <license-p>This dataset is made available under the Open Database License (http://opendatacommons.org/licenses/odbl/1.0/). The Open Database License (ODbL) is a license agreement intended to allow users to freely share, modify, and use this Dataset while maintaining this same freedom for others, provided that the original source and author(s) are credited.</license-p>
          </license>
        </permissions>
        <attrib specific-use="authors">Jose D. Zúñiga, Morgan R. Gostel, Daniel G. Mulcahy, Katharine Barker, Asia Hill, Maryam Sedaghatpour, Samantha Q. Vo, Vicki A. Funk, Jonathan A. Coddington</attrib>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </back>
</article>
