<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.614.10200</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title><italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>, a new species of butterflyfish (<tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="order">Perciformes</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="family">Chaetodontidae</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>) from the Hawaiian Archipelago</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Pyle</surname>
            <given-names>Richard L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Kosaki</surname>
            <given-names>Randall K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Bernice P. Bishop Museum, 1525 Bernice Street, Honolulu, Hawai‘i 96817, USA</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="A2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>NOAA Papahānaumokuākea Marine National Monument, 1845 Wasp Blvd, Building 176, Honolulu, Hawai‘i 96818, USA</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="corresp">
          <p>Corresponding author: Richard L. Pyle (<email xlink:type="simple">deepreef@bishopmuseum.org</email>)</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="edited-by">
          <p>Academic editor: P. Stoev</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>6</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <issue>614</issue>
      <fpage>137</fpage>
      <lpage>152</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Richard L. Pyle, Randall K. Kosaki</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0" xlink:type="simple">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY 4.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri content-type="zoobank" xlink:type="simple">http://zoobank.org/5E635B1B-2764-4CAC-A0FF-5FC02F4E40ED</self-uri>
      <abstract>
        <label>Abstract</label>
        <p>A new species of the butterflyfish genus <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> is described from specimens collected at a depth of 55–61 m off Pearl and Hermes Atoll, Northwestern Hawaiian Islands. This species has been observed by mixed-gas divers and from submersibles at depths ranging from 45–187 m throughout the Hawaiian Archipelago, with shallower sightings in the Northwestern Hawaiian Islands and deeper in the Main Hawaiian Islands. It is similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">guezei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Maugé and Bauchot 1976</xref>) from the western Indian Ocean, and at least one other undescribed species of <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> from Palau, differing from these species in the number of soft dorsal-fin rays, size of head, and body depth. There are also differences in the life color, and a substantial genetic difference from the Palauan species (d » .08 in mtDNA cytochrome oxidase I).</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <label>Keywords</label>
        <kwd>Mesophotic Coral Ecosystem</kwd>
        <kwd>Closed-Circuit Rebreather</kwd>
        <kwd>Endemic</kwd>
        <kwd>Papahānaumokuākea Marine National Monument</kwd>
        <!--PageBreak-->
      </kwd-group>
    <funding-group><award-group><funding-source><named-content content-type="project_title">National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA)</named-content><named-content content-type="project_identifier">1522808</named-content><named-content content-type="project_funder_id">501100000314</named-content><named-content content-type="project_funder_name">ABBEY AWARDS</named-content><named-content content-type="project_funder_doi">http://doi.org/10.13039/501100000314</named-content></funding-source></award-group></funding-group></article-meta>
    <notes>
      <sec sec-type="Citation" id="SECID0EYF">
        <title>Citation</title>
        <p>Pyle RL, Kosaki RK (2016) <italic>Prognathodes basabei</italic>, a new species of butterflyfish (Perciformes, Chaetodontidae) from the Hawaiian Archipelago. ZooKeys 614: 137–152. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3897/zookeys.614.10200">10.3897/zookeys.614.10200</ext-link></p>
      </sec>
    </notes>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="Introduction" id="SECID0EFG">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> Gill, 1862 (type species <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Chelmo</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">pelta</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> Günther, 1860 = <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Chaetodon</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">aculeatus</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> Poey, 1860) currently includes eleven valid species: seven from the Atlantic, two from the tropical eastern Pacific, and two from the Indian Ocean and western Pacific. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Pyle and Chave (1994)</xref> first reported the presence of a species of this genus in the Hawaiian Islands at depths of 106–187 m, based on video and observations from research submersibles operated by the <abbrev content-type="institution" id="ABBRID0EKH"><def><p>Hawaii Undersea Research Laboratory </p></def>(HURL)</abbrev>. They noted its similarity to <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">guezei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> (Mauge and Bauchot 1976), a species then known only from the two type specimens collected at a depth of 80 m off Réunion Island in the western Indian Ocean.</p>
      <p>While conducting an exploratory dive using a mixed-gas closed-circuit rebreather off the south shore of O‘ahu (Main Hawaiian Islands) on 17 May 1998, the senior author (RLP) observed (but was unable to collect) a group of three <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> near an undercut limestone ledge at a depth of 114 m. Two weeks later (30 May 1998), with the assistance of Peter K. Basabe, RLP collected the first specimen of this species at a depth of 120 m near Kealakekua Bay on the Kona coast of the island of Hawai‘i (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">TenBruggencate 1998</xref>). The following day he collected several more individuals at a depth of 115 m near the site of the observation of 17 May (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Allen et al. 1998</xref>). All of the collected individuals were brought to the surface alive and maintained in captivity. Unfortunately, when they eventually died, only one was preserved, and it was too badly deteriorated to serve as a type specimen.</p>
      <p>In the years that followed, several more individuals of this species were collected from depths of 115–125 m around O‘ahu by mixed-gas rebreather divers. All were maintained in aquaria until their deaths, but none were properly preserved as suitable type specimens. On 27 April 2007, RLP collected two individuals of a similar species of <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> at a depth of 116 m at Palau (Republic of Belau), in the western Pacific. Although some color differences between the Palauan and Hawaiian fishes were noted, the authors felt it was necessary to obtain specimens of the Hawaiian population for comparison of morphological and genetic characters before determining whether they are the same species.</p>
      <p>In August of 2009, after the establishment of the Papahānaumokuākea Marine National Monument in the Northwestern Hawaiian Islands, the <abbrev id="ABBRID0EYAAC"><def><p>U.S. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration </p></def>(NOAA)</abbrev> began a series of annual surveys of <abbrev id="ABBRID0ECBAC"><def><p>Mesophotic Coral Ecosystems </p></def>(MCEs)</abbrev> within the Monument using mixed-gas diving technology. During the first of these surveys, the authors collected a group of three individuals of the unidentified <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> at a depth of 61 m off the SW side of Pearl and Hermes Atoll. Unfortunately, tissue samples taken from these specimens were misplaced, so it was not possible to make genetic comparisons with the Palauan population.</p>
      <p>Finally, in September of 2015, the authors were able to collect three more specimens at the same site off Pearl and Hermes Atoll where the three specimens had been collected in 2009, and obtain additional tissue samples for genetic analyses. Based on <!--PageBreak-->an examination of both morphological and genetic characters of the six Hawaiian specimens, as well as comparisons with the two specimens from Palau and <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">guezei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>, we can now confirm that the Hawaiian population represents a new species, distinct from both <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">guezei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> and the undescribed Palauan species. We herein describe the Hawaiian population as the new species, <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="methods" id="SECID0ERCAC">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <p>Specimens were collected with hand nets during deep dives using mixed-gas, closed-circuit rebreathers. Additional observations, videos and images of this species were made from the two <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Pisces</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> submersibles operated by the Hawaii Undersea Research Laboratory (<abbrev content-type="institution" xlink:title="Hawaii Undersea Research Laboratory" id="ABBRID0E5CAC">HURL</abbrev>, at the University of Hawai‘i), and by mixed-gas rebreather divers in the Main Hawaiian Islands and Northwestern Hawaiian Islands.</p>
      <p><abbrev id="ABBRID0EKDAC"><def><p>Standard length </p></def>(SL)</abbrev> was measured from the tip of the snout to the caudal-fin base. <abbrev id="ABBRID0EXDAC"><def><p>Total length </p></def>(TL)</abbrev> was measured from the tip of the snout to the posterior edge of the caudal fin. Head length was measured from the tip of the snout to the posterior-most edge of the fleshy flap near the upper end of the gill opening. Body depth is the greatest depth of body measured as a vertical from the ventral edge of the abdomen to the upper edge of scaled fleshy sheath of the dorsal fin (typically from about fourth or fifth dorsal spine). Width of the body is the maximum width. Snout length is the distance from the tip of the snout to the closest point on the bony orbit. Predorsal length is the distance from the tip of the snout to the angle formed by the scaled fleshy sheath at the insertion point of the first dorsal-fin spine, when erected. Preanal length is the distance from the tip of the snout to angle formed by the scaled fleshy sheath at the insertion point of the first anal-fin spine, when erected. The base of the dorsal fin is measured from the extreme base of the first dorsal-fin spine to the extreme base of the last dorsal-fin soft ray. The base of the anal fin is measured from the extreme base of the first anal-fin spine to the extreme base of the last anal-fin soft ray. Orbit diameter is the maximum diameter of the bony orbit. Interorbital width is the width of the bony interorbital space. Depth of the caudal peduncle is the least depth. Pelvic-fin spine length was measured from the extreme base of the pelvic-fin spine to its distal tip. Pelvic fin length was only measured on specimens with intact filamentous extensions of the first pelvic-fin soft ray, and represents the length of that ray from its extreme base to the distal tip of the filamentous extension. Length of spines and soft rays of dorsal and anal fins were measured from the extreme base to the most distal tip. Caudal fin length was defined as the difference between <abbrev xlink:title="Total length" id="ABBRID0EBEAC">TL</abbrev> and <abbrev xlink:title="Standard length" id="ABBRID0EIEAC">SL</abbrev>. Pectoral fin length was measured as the longest fin ray, from its extreme base to its distal tip.</p>
      <p>The last dorsal- and anal-fin soft rays are branched to the base and were counted as a single ray. Caudal-fin ray counts include small unsegmented and rudimentary rays. Pectoral-fin ray counts include first and last unsegmented rays. Pored lateral-line scale counts include only those scales with pores. Scale-row counts above and below lateral line to origins of dorsal and anal fins (respectively) include small truncate scales at bases <!--PageBreak-->of respective fins. Vertebral counts include the first vertebra fused to the skull, and the last vertebra fused to the hypural plate.</p>
      <p>All counts and measurements except vertebrae were made directly from specimens. Measurements were made using dial calipers with +/- 0.05 mm precision. Lengths of dorsal- and anal-fin spines and soft rays were made with the aid of a bright light transmitted from behind the fins to reveal the position of their extreme bases. Vertebral counts were made from x-radiographs.</p>
      <p>Head length, depth of body, width of body, snout length, predorsal length, preanal length, length of dorsal-fin and anal-fin bases, orbit diameter, interorbital width, caudal peduncle depth, and lengths of fin spines and rays are expressed as percent of <abbrev xlink:title="Standard length" id="ABBRID0EWEAC">SL</abbrev>. Counts and measurements for paratypes, if different from the holotype, are presented in parentheses after the value for the holotype.</p>
      <p>The holotype and three paratypes have been deposited at the Bernice Pauahi <named-content xlink:type="simple" content-type="institution" xlink:href="http://grbio.org/institution/bishop-museum" id="NCID0E6EAC">Bishop Museum</named-content> fish collection, Honolulu (<named-content content-type="dwc:institutional_code">BPBM</named-content>), and paratypes have been deposited at the <abbrev content-type="institution" id="ABBRID0ENFAC"><def><p><named-content xlink:type="simple" content-type="institution" xlink:href="http://grbio.org/institution/california-academy-sciences" id="NCID0ESFAC">California Academy of Sciences</named-content> fish collection, San Francisco </p></def>(CAS)</abbrev>, and the <abbrev content-type="institution" id="ABBRID0EAGAC"><def><p>U.S. <named-content xlink:type="simple" content-type="institution" xlink:href="http://grbio.org/institution/national-museum" id="NCID0EGGAC">National Museum of Natural History</named-content>, Washington, D.C. </p></def>(USNM)</abbrev>.</p>
      <p>Tissue samples were obtained from the holotype and two paratypes (<named-content content-type="dwc:institutional_code">CAS</named-content> 242132 and <named-content content-type="dwc:institutional_code">USNM</named-content> 440272). DNA barcodes (<abbrev id="ABBRID0E3HAC"><def><p>cytochrome c oxidase I; </p></def>COI</abbrev>) were sequenced following the protocol described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Copus et al. (2015)</xref>. GenBank accession numbers and <abbrev id="ABBRID0EIIAC"><def><p>Barcode of Life Database </p></def>(BOLD)</abbrev> identifiers for DNA sequences are presented along with museum catalog numbers for type material and non-type specimens.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="Taxonomy" id="SECID0ESIAC">
      <title>Taxonomy</title>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
        <tp:treatment-meta>
          <kwd-group>
            <label>Taxon classification</label>
            <kwd>
              <named-content content-type="kingdom" xlink:type="simple">Animalia</named-content>
            </kwd>
            <kwd>
              <named-content content-type="order" xlink:type="simple">Perciformes</named-content>
            </kwd>
            <kwd>
              <named-content content-type="family" xlink:type="simple">Chaetodontidae</named-content>
            </kwd>
          </kwd-group>
        </tp:treatment-meta>
        <tp:nomenclature>
          <tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part>
            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part>
            <object-id content-type="zoobank" xlink:type="simple">http://zoobank.org/A843AA98-2312-4E9E-B1EC-E28B5478085E</object-id>
          </tp:taxon-name>
          <tp:taxon-authority>Pyle &amp; Kosaki</tp:taxon-authority>
          <tp:taxon-status>sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
          <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">, 2</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">, 3</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">, 4</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">, 5</xref>
          <tp:nomenclature-citation-list><tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name><comment> sp. 1; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Allen et al. 1998</xref>: 250.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> “<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part>”</tp:taxon-name><comment>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Randall 2007</xref>: 291.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
          </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
        </tp:nomenclature>
        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type locality" id="SECID0ENLAC">
          <title>Type locality.</title>
          <p>Northwestern Hawaiian Islands, Pearl and Hermes Atoll, southwest side, “<tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name> Point”, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates"><named-content content-type="geo-json" specific-use="{&quot;type&quot;:&quot;Point&quot;,&quot;coordinates&quot;:[-175.985900,27.764100]}" id="NCID0E3LAC">27.7641°N, 175.9859°W</named-content></named-content>.</p>
        </tp:treatment-sec>
        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype" id="SECID0EBMAC">
          <title>Holotype.</title>
          <p>
            <named-content content-type="dwc:institutional_code">BPBM</named-content> 41290, female, GenBank <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="KX783257" xlink:type="simple">KX783257</ext-link>, Barcode of Life PROBA001-16, 93.4 mm <abbrev xlink:title="Standard length" id="ABBRID0EPMAC">SL</abbrev>, Northwestern Hawaiian Islands, Pearl and Hermes Atoll, southwest side, “<tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name> Point”, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates"><named-content content-type="geo-json" specific-use="{&quot;type&quot;:&quot;Point&quot;,&quot;coordinates&quot;:[-175.985900,27.764100]}" id="NCID0E6MAC">27.7641°N, 175.9859°W</named-content></named-content>, 61 m, 13 September 2015, R. L. Pyle, aboard <abbrev xlink:title="U.S. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration" id="ABBRID0EENAC">NOAA</abbrev> ship <italic>Hi‘ialakai</italic> (Cruise: HA-15-05), hand nets, under limestone ledge (ancient seashore). Collected as part of a group of three associated individuals (along with <named-content content-type="dwc:institutional_code">CAS</named-content> 242132 and <named-content content-type="dwc:institutional_code">USNM</named-content> 440272).</p>
        </tp:treatment-sec>
        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes" id="SECID0EEOAC">
          <title>Paratypes.</title>
          <p>
            <named-content content-type="dwc:institutional_code">BPBM</named-content> 41285, 3 specimens: 97.7–106.3 mm <abbrev xlink:title="Standard length" id="ABBRID0ENOAC">SL</abbrev>, same location, habitat, collector, vessel and collecting method as holotype, 55 m, 17 August 2009, Cruise: HI-09-06; <named-content content-type="dwc:institutional_code">CAS</named-content> 242132, GenBank <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="KX783255" xlink:type="simple">KX783255</ext-link>, Barcode of Life PROBA003-16, 102.5 <!--PageBreak-->mm <abbrev xlink:title="Standard length" id="ABBRID0EGPAC">SL</abbrev>, same location, depth, habitat, collector, vessel, cruise and collecting method as holotype, 14 September 2015; <named-content content-type="dwc:institutional_code">USNM</named-content> 440272, GenBank <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="KX783256" xlink:type="simple">KX783256</ext-link>, Barcode of Life PROBA002-16, same data as holotype.</p>
        </tp:treatment-sec>
        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Non-type specimen" id="SECID0E1PAC">
          <title>Non-type specimen.</title>
          <p>
            <named-content content-type="dwc:institutional_code">BPBM</named-content> 38441, 82 mm <abbrev xlink:title="Standard length" id="ABBRID0EEAAE">SL</abbrev>, Hawaiian Islands, O‘ahu, south shore, 116 m, 31 May 1998, R. L. Pyle, hand nets, along limestone ledge (specimen died in captivity and partially deteriorated).</p>
        </tp:treatment-sec>
        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis" id="SECID0ELAAE">
          <title>Diagnosis.</title>
          <p>A species of <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic>sensu</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Smith et al. 2003</xref>) distinguished by the following combination of characters: dorsal-fin soft rays 21 or 22; anal-fin soft rays 16 or 17; head 2.63–2.80 in <abbrev xlink:title="Standard length" id="ABBRID0E5AAE">SL</abbrev>; body depth 1.58–1.69 in <abbrev xlink:title="Standard length" id="ABBRID0EFBAE">SL</abbrev>; pelvic-fin spine length 3.63–4.07 in <abbrev xlink:title="Standard length" id="ABBRID0EMBAE">SL</abbrev>; color in life pale yellow dorsally fading to white ventrally (sometimes entirely white) with three black bands with narrow white margins on each side of the body, the first band originating at and including the first dorsal-fin spine, extending diagonally to the eye and continuing horizontally as an orangish brown stripe from the eye to the tip of the snout, the second band originating at and including the fourth to sixth dorsal-fin spines, extending vertically at a slightly posterior angle to the ventral surface of the abdomen just anterior to the anus, tapering slightly and curving slightly posteriorly below the pectoral fin, and the third band originating at and including the last four to five dorsal-fin spines and first four to five dorsal-fin soft rays, extending vertically at a slightly posterior angle to and including the first several anal-fin soft rays, a narrow orange band on the dorso-posterior margin of the operculum, extending ventrally the posterior angle of the operculum, an oblong orange spot with some dark pigmentation on the upper <!--PageBreak-->one-third of the pectoral-fin axis, pelvic fins white on the spine and anterior one-third of fin, and bright orange on the posterior two-thirds of fin, a bright orange submarginal band with narrow white posterior margin extending along the posterior margins of the soft portions of the dorsal and anal fins, and continuing across the caudal peduncle.</p>
        </tp:treatment-sec>
        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description" id="SECID0EVBAE">
          <title>Description.</title>
          <p>Dorsal fin XIII (XII in two paratypes),21 (22 in one paratype), last soft ray branched to base; anal fin III,16 (17 in one paratype), last soft ray branched to base; pectoral-fin rays 16 (15 in one paratype); pelvic-fin rays I,5; principal branched caudal rays 15, upper procurrent unbranched caudal rays 4, lower procurrent unbranched caudal rays 3; pored lateral-line scales 26 (24–28); scale rows above lateral line to origin of dorsal fin 10 (11 in all but one paratype); scale rows below lateral line to origin of anal fin 24 (21–27); gill rakers on upper limb 6, on lower limb 9 (10 in one paratype); vertebrae 24.</p>
          <p>Body deep, the depth 1.58 (1.61–1.69) in <abbrev xlink:title="Standard length" id="ABBRID0E3BAE">SL</abbrev>, and compressed, the width 4.05 (3.80–4.33) in depth; head length 2.63 (2.65–2.80) in <abbrev xlink:title="Standard length" id="ABBRID0EDCAE">SL</abbrev>; snout produced, its length 2.35 (2.19–2.62) in head; orbit diameter 3.59 (3.50–3.83) in head; interorbital slightly convex, the least bony width 4.18 (3.85–4.28) in head; least depth of caudal peduncle 4.33 (4.00–4.33) in head.</p>
          <p>Mouth small, the upper jaw 2.77 in head, slightly diagonal, the gape forming an angle of about 20° to the horizontal, the upper jaw slightly protruding; teeth in jaws densely setiform, the longest 7.8 in orbit diameter; nostrils anterior to the eye horizontally in line with the top of the iris, the anterior in a short membranous tube with a well-developed posterior flap, the posterior slightly larger, ovate, with a low fleshy rim. Lower edge of lacrimal smooth; margin of preopercle finely serrate; margins of other opercular bones smooth.</p>
          <p>Lateral line forming a broad arc, ending below the base of the third to fifth soft dorsal ray and within the second black band on the body. Scales ctenoid, moderately large on body except for chest and near origins of dorsal and anal fins, where small; head fully scaled except anterior portions of both jaws and around nostrils, the scales on the head small; scales on fleshy sheath surrounding base of dorsal and anal fins moderately large anteriorly and proximally, reducing in size posteriorly and distally; scales on caudal peduncle and covering base of caudal fin small.</p>
          <p>Origin of dorsal fin slightly posterior to upper end of gill opening, its base 1.45 (1.43–1.52) in <abbrev xlink:title="Standard length" id="ABBRID0EOCAE">SL</abbrev>; first dorsal-fin spine the shortest, its length 3.09 (2.49–3.68) in head; second dorsal-fin spine 1.27 (1.42–1.98, broken in one paratype) in head; third dorsal-fin spine the longest, its length 0.93 (0.94–1.11, broken in one paratype) in head; fourth dorsal-fin spine nearly as long as the third, its length 1.04 (1.03–1.13, broken in one paratype, deformed in one paratype) in head; fifth dorsal-fin spine shorter, its length 1.20 (1.14–1.23, broken in one paratype) in head; dorsal-fin spines progressively shorter posteriorly, the last 1.80 (1.80–2.06) in head; membranes between anterior dorsal-fin spines deeply incised, progressively less so posteriorly; first dorsal-fin soft ray the longest, approximately the same length as the last dorsal-fin spine, 1.80 (1.70–1.88) in head, dorsal-fin soft rays progressively shorter posteriorly; first anal-fin spine the shortest, its length 2.54 (2.44–3.10) in head; second anal-fin spine the longest, its length 1.31 (1.16–1.31) in head; third anal-fin spine 1.52 (1.39–1.62) in head; <!--PageBreak-->first anal-fin soft ray the longest, its length 1.35 (1.39–1.62) in head, anal-fin soft rays progressively shorter posteriorly; caudal fin slightly convex with a slight concavity at the mid-line, its length 1.79 (1.83–2.00) in head; pectoral fins 1.37 (1.26–1.43) in head; pelvic spine 1.38 (1.36–1.51) in head; first soft ray of pelvic fin with a filamentous extension, its length 1.08 (1.19, broken in all but one paratype) in head.</p>
          <p>Color in life as in Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>. Body pale yellow dorsally fading to white ventrally and on the thorax and lower head (color of body sometimes lacking pale yellow coloration); three prominent black bands on each side of the body with narrow white margins, the first band originating at and including the first dorsal-fin spine, extending diagonally to the eye and continuing horizontally as an orangish brown stripe from the eye to the tip of the snout, the second band originating at and including the fourth to sixth dorsal-fin spines, extending vertically at a slightly posterior angle to the ventral surface of the abdomen just anterior to the anus, tapering slightly and curving slightly posteriorly below the pectoral fin, and the third band originating at and including last four to five dorsal-fin spines and first four to five soft dorsal rays, extending vertically at a slightly posterior angle to and including the first several anal soft rays, the bands becoming dark orangish brown distally on the dorsal fin; a narrow orangish brown stripe extending from the dorsal side of the snout broadening dorsally on the nape to a point just above the interorbital space, becoming darker dorsally; a narrow orange band on the dorso-posterior margin of the operculum, extending ventrally to the posterior angle of the operculum, an oblong orange spot with some dark pigmentation on <!--PageBreak-->the upper one-third of the pectoral-fin axis; pelvic fins white on the spine and anterior one-third of fin, and bright orange on the posterior two-thirds of fin; a bright orange submarginal band with narrow white posterior margin extending along the posterior margins of the soft portions of the dorsal and anal fins and continuing across the caudal peduncle; caudal fin and pectoral fins translucent.</p>
          <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 1.</label>
            <caption>
              <p>Holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> (<named-content content-type="dwc:institutional_code">BPBM</named-content> 41290), collected at a depth of 61 m off Pearl and Hermes Atoll, Northwestern Hawaiian Islands. Photo by R. L. Pyle.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="zookeys-614-e10200-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="oo_101666.jpg"/>
          </fig>
          <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 2.</label>
            <caption>
              <p>Paratype of <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> (<named-content content-type="dwc:institutional_code">BPBM</named-content> 41285-1), collected at a depth of 55 m off Pearl and Hermes Atoll, Northwestern Hawaiian Islands. Photo by R. L. Pyle.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="zookeys-614-e10200-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="oo_101667.jpg"/>
          </fig>
          <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 3.</label>
            <caption>
              <p>
          <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> at a depth of approximately 55 m off Pearl and Hermes Atoll, Northwestern Hawaiian Islands. Photo by G. McFall.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="zookeys-614-e10200-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="oo_101668.jpg"/>
          </fig>
          <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 4.</label>
            <caption>
              <p>
          <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> at a depth of 90 m off Pearl and Hermes Atoll, Northwestern Hawaiian Islands. Photo by R. L. Pyle.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="zookeys-614-e10200-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="oo_101671.jpg"/>
          </fig>
          <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 5.</label>
            <caption>
              <p>A group of three <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> at a depth of 90 m off Pearl and Hermes Atoll, Northwestern Hawaiian Islands. Photo by R. L. Pyle.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="zookeys-614-e10200-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="oo_101673.jpg"/>
          </fig>
          <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 6.</label>
            <caption>
              <p>
          <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">guezei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> at a depth of 117 m off Sodwana Bay, South Africa. Photo by R. L. Pyle.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="zookeys-614-e10200-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="oo_101675.jpg"/>
          </fig>
          <p>Color in alcohol similar to life color, except body a uniform dull yellow, bands dark brown, and orange areas pale brown.</p>
          <p>A single juvenile, about 25 mm <abbrev xlink:title="Standard length" id="ABBRID0EYHAE">SL</abbrev>, was observed by RLP at a depth of 120 m during a dive off Pearl Harbor, O‘ahu on 16 August 1998. The general body shape and color pattern were the same as for adults.</p>
          <p>Morphometric data for selected characters of type specimens are provided in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>.</p>
          <table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Table 1.</label>
            <caption>
              <p>Morphometric and meristic data for selected characters of type specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>. Values of morphometric data (other than <abbrev xlink:title="Total length" id="ABBRID0EYIAE">TL</abbrev> and <abbrev xlink:title="Standard length" id="ABBRID0E6IAE">SL</abbrev>) are represented as % of <abbrev xlink:title="Standard length" id="ABBRID0EGJAE">SL</abbrev>.</p>
            </caption>
            <table id="TID0E2GAG" rules="all">
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holotype</th>
                  <th rowspan="1" colspan="5">Paratypes</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Morphometrics</th>
                  <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="dwc:institutional_code">BPBM</named-content> 41290</th>
                  <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="dwc:institutional_code">BPBM</named-content> 41285-1</th>
                  <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="dwc:institutional_code">BPBM</named-content> 41285-2</th>
                  <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="dwc:institutional_code">BPBM</named-content> 41285-3</th>
                  <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="dwc:institutional_code">CAS</named-content> 242132</th>
                  <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <named-content content-type="dwc:institutional_code">USNM</named-content> 440272</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</th>
                  <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</th>
                  <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</th>
                  <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</th>
                  <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</th>
                  <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</th>
                  <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
              <abbrev id="ABBRID0ERMAE">
                <def>
                  <p> Total length </p>
                </def>(TL)</abbrev> in mm</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">113.2</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">125.5</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">123.1</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">117.8</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">122.5</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">119.6</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
              <abbrev id="ABBRID0EVNAE">
                <def>
                  <p> Standard length </p>
                </def>(SL)</abbrev> in mm</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.4</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106.3</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102.2</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.7</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102.5</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Head length</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body depth</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body width</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Snout length</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predorsal length</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Preanal length</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Base of dorsal fin</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Base of anal fin</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Orbit diameter</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.8</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.8</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interorbital Width</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caudal Peduncle Depth</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.7</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.9</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.7</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pelvic Spine</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.3</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pelvic Fin</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">First Dorsal Spine length</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Second Dorsal Spine length</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">broken</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Third Dorsal Spine length</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">broken</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fourth Dorsal Spine length</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">damaged</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">broken</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fifth Dorsal Spine length</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">broken</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Last Dorsal Spine length</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longest Dorsal Ray length</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">First Anal Spine length</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Second Anal Spine length</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Third Anal Spine length</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longest anal ray length</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caudal fin length</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pectoral fin length</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
              <bold>Meristics</bold>
            </td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorsal Spines</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">XIII</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">XIII</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">XII</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">XII</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">XIII</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">XIII</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorsal rays</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anal Spines</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anal Rays</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pectoral Rays</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caudal Rays</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pored lateral line scales</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorsal scale rows</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ventral scale rows</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gill rakers</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6+9</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6+9</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6+9</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6+10</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                  <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </table-wrap>
        </tp:treatment-sec>
        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution" id="SECID0EGIAG">
          <title>Distribution.</title>
          <p>
            <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> has been observed or collected at depths of 45–187 m at several locations throughout the Hawaiian Archipelago, including both the main Hawaiian Islands (Hawai‘I, O‘ahu, Penguin Banks) and the <abbrev id="ABBRID0EWIAG"><def><p>Northwestern Hawaiian Islands </p></def>(NWHI</abbrev>; French Frigate Shoals, Lisianski, Pearl and Hermes Atoll, Midway Atoll, Kure Atoll). No observations of this species were made during 61 submersible dives or eight mixed-gas rebreather dives to appropriate depths at Johnston Atoll (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Randall et al. 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Wagner et al. 2014</xref>), nor has any similar fish been observed or collected anywhere in the central or eastern Pacific. Thus, it appears that <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> is endemic to the Hawaiian Archipelago (although further exploration of <abbrev xlink:title="Mesophotic Coral Ecosystems" id="ABBRID0EOJAG">MCEs</abbrev> in nearby regions may yet reveal its presence elsewhere). This is consistent with the observation that fish assemblages on deep coral reefs have proportionally more endemic species than on shallow reefs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Pyle 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Kane et al. 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Kosaki et al. 2016</xref>).</p>
        </tp:treatment-sec>
        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="habitat" id="SECID0E5JAG">
          <title>Habitat.</title>
          <p>
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Pyle and Chave (1994</xref>: 92) described the habitat for this species based on videotaped observations from submersibles as follows:</p>
          <p>
            <italic>Eighteen (56%) of the observed [fish] were in areas of basalt substrata (e.g., basalt talus, blocky lava, lava tubes and pillows, basalt boulders), 13 (41 %) were in limestone habitats (primarily limestone holes and ledges), and one fish was sighted on a large (2-m diam.) water pipe. Four of the fish were in the vicinity of an unidentified antipatharian coral, three near</italic> <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Cirrhipathes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">spiralis</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name> <italic>(Linnaeus), and one near</italic> <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Antipathes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">dichotoma</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name> <italic>Pallas</italic>.</p>
          <p>Subsequent observations of this species by divers and submersible dives, totaling several dozen individuals mostly off O‘ahu and various sites within the <abbrev xlink:title="Northwestern Hawaiian Islands" id="ABBRID0EELAG">NWHI</abbrev>, were all found in association with limestone ledges and discontinuities representing ancient shorelines (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). In almost all cases, the fish were found underneath, inside of, or in close proximity to small undercut overhangs or caves, often swimming upside-down in association with the roof of the overhangs and caves. There are no obvious associations with other species, such as antipathinarian corals, other corals and sessile invertebrates, or particular fish species; although certain other fish species, such as than anthias <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Odontanthias</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">fuscipinnis</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> (Jenkins, 1901) and the wrasse <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Bodianus</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">sanguineus</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> (Jordan &amp; Evermann, 1903), tend to occupy the same depth and habitat.</p>
        </tp:treatment-sec>
        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology" id="SECID0EEMAG">
          <title>Etymology.</title>
          <p>We take great pleasure in naming this species <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>, in honor of Peter K. Basabe, long-time diver, aquarium fish collector and resident of Kona, Hawai‘i, both for his role in the collection of the first specimen of this new species in 1998, <!--PageBreak-->and more generally for his extensive contributions and assistance to many researchers (especially the authors) in the ichthyological community.</p>
        </tp:treatment-sec>
        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Morphological comparisons" id="SECID0EWMAG">
          <title>Morphological comparisons.</title>
          <p>
            <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> appears to be most similar in color and morphology to an undescribed <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> species collected at a similar depth in Palau. These two species differ from each other in number of dorsal-fin soft rays (21–22 for <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>, compared to 17–19 for the Palau species) and anal-fin soft rays (16–17, compared to 15). <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> also has a smaller head (2.63–2.80 in <abbrev xlink:title="Standard length" id="ABBRID0EBOAG">SL</abbrev>, compared to 2.48–2.49 in <abbrev xlink:title="Standard length" id="ABBRID0EIOAG">SL</abbrev>), deeper body (1.58–1.69 in <abbrev xlink:title="Standard length" id="ABBRID0EPOAG">SL</abbrev>, compared to 1.71–1.76 in <abbrev xlink:title="Standard length" id="ABBRID0EWOAG">SL</abbrev>), and shorter pelvic-fin spine (3.63–4.07 in <abbrev xlink:title="Standard length" id="ABBRID0E4OAG">SL</abbrev>, compared to 4.18–4.46 in <abbrev xlink:title="Standard length" id="ABBRID0EEPAG">SL</abbrev>) than the Palau species. The two species also differ in certain aspects of life color. The anterior edge of the second black band of the Palau species originates at the third dorsal-fin spine, whereas this band originates on the fourth dorsal-fin spine in <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>. Moreover, both of the dark bands on the Palau species are proportionally broader dorsally, tapering more substantially ventrally than in <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>. Also, the orangish coloration on the pelvic fins and posterior margin of the soft dorsal and anal fins of the Palau species are much darker and brownish than in <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
          <p>
            <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> is also similar in color and morphology to <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">guezei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> from the western Indian Ocean. It differs from that species morphologically in number of dorsal-fin soft rays (21–22 for <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>, compared to 20 for <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">guezei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>), head size (2.63–2.80 in <abbrev xlink:title="Standard length" id="ABBRID0ETRAG">SL</abbrev>, compared to 2.47–2.48 in <abbrev xlink:title="Standard length" id="ABBRID0E1RAG">SL</abbrev>), body depth (1.58–1.69 in <abbrev xlink:title="Standard length" id="ABBRID0EBSAG">SL</abbrev>, compared to 1.87–1.95 in <abbrev xlink:title="Standard length" id="ABBRID0EISAG">SL</abbrev>), and shorter pelvic-fin spine (3.63–4.07 in <abbrev xlink:title="Standard length" id="ABBRID0EPSAG">SL</abbrev>, compared to 4.21–4.33 in <abbrev xlink:title="Standard length" id="ABBRID0EWSAG">SL</abbrev>). There are also <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->several differences in life color between the two species. In particular, <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">guezei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>) has more pronounced and discrete yellow bars on the body between the black bands, compared with more diffuse and paler yellow in <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>. As with the Palau species, the anterior edge of the second black band of the <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">guezei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> originates at the third dorsal-fin spine, whereas this band originates on the fourth dorsal-fin spine in <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>, and the two black bands on the body of <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">guezei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> taper even more substantially than they do in the Palau species, with the dorsal end of the posterior band in <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">guezei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> covering the last five dorsal-fin spines, compared with the last four dorsal-fin spines on <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>. Also, the orangish coloration on the pelvic fins and posterior margin of the soft dorsal and anal fins of <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">guezei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> are much paler and yellowish than in <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
        </tp:treatment-sec>
        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Genetic comparisons" id="SECID0E6VAG">
          <title>Genetic comparisons.</title>
          <p>Genetic comparisons provide another compelling justification for regarding <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> as distinct from the Palau species. The vertebrate mtDNA barcode (cytochrome oxidase I) sequences obtained from the holotype and two paratypes of <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>, compared to specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. collected in Palau, reveal 8% uncorrected sequence divergence. This is consistent with species-level divergences in other fish taxa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Johns and Avise 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Bellwood et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Fessler and Westneat 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Randall and Rocha 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Rocha 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Rocha et al. 2008</xref>). The accepted mtDNA clock rate of approximately 2% per million years in fishes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Bowen et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Reece et al. 2010</xref>) indicates divergence between these species on the order of 4 million years.</p>
          <p>No tissue samples or DNA sequences have been reported for <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">guezei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>, but given the geographic distributions of <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">guezei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> in the western Indian Ocean, the Palau species, and <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>, we anticipate that the genetic divergence between <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">guezei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> will prove to be even deeper than that between <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> and the Palau species.</p>
          <!--PageBreak-->
        </tp:treatment-sec>
        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion" id="SECID0ED1AG">
          <title>Discussion.</title>
          <p>
            <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> is an example of the conspicuous new fish species that have been discovered on deep coral reefs over the past two decades, mostly involving the use of modern mixed-gas closed-circuit rebreather diving technology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Pyle 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">2000</xref>). There has been increased attention focused on mesophotic coral ecosystems (<abbrev xlink:title="Mesophotic Coral Ecosystems" id="ABBRID0E21AG">MCEs</abbrev>), coral-reef habitat at depths of approximately 30–150 m in tropical regions worldwide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Hinderstein et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Baker et al. 2016</xref>).</p>
          <p>One particularly unusual characteristic of this species is the tendency for it to be found in groups of three individuals. Although <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Pyle and Chave (1994)</xref> reported that most videotaped observations from submersibles involved apparent pairs or solitary individuals, in most cases these observations were incidental to the research focus on the submersible dives, so no concerted effort was made to determine the total number of individuals at each sighting. Every observation of adults of this species by the authors during mixed-gas dives in both the main Hawaiian Islands and <abbrev xlink:title="Northwestern Hawaiian Islands" id="ABBRID0EN2AG">NWHI</abbrev> (nearly two dozen instances), as well as observations by RLP during several submersible dives off south O‘ahu in 2011, involved groups of three individuals; the only exception was the solitary juvenile observed by RLP in 1998. Only two individuals of the Palau species were observed together, and none of the approximately ten individuals of <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">guezei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> observed by RLP at depths of 115–120 m off Sodwana Bay in 2011 were found in a group of three. Butterflyfishes (<tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="family">Chaetodontidae</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>) in general are known to display a variety of social and mating systems, including monogamous pairs, harems, and schools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Reese 1975</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Yabuta and Berumen 2013</xref>). Territoriality and the distribution of food resources are important determinants of these social systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Hourigan 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Pratchett et al. 2013</xref>). Groups of three individuals as a primary social grouping have not been noted in other chaetodontid species. The six type specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> were found as two groups of three individuals. In both cases, the groupings included a single female and two males. More samples are necessary to determine whether such associations represent loose social groupings, territorial behavior, a mating system, or coincidence.</p>
          <p>Another interesting aspect of this new species is the strikingly similar color pattern it shares with both the Palau species, and with <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">guezei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>, in contrast to the deep genetic divergence that exists between the Hawaiian and Palauan specimens. It will be interesting to compare the genetics of <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">guezei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> once tissue samples can be obtained, and as previously noted, we expect the genetic divergence to be similarly deep. A more thorough analysis and discussion of genetic comparisons between <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> and the Palauan species will be included in the forthcoming description of the latter species.</p>
          <p>
            <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> is the twelfth recognized member of the genus, a group generally inhabiting deeper habitats than most other chaetodontid species. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Nalbant (1995)</xref> suggested that the group may have an antitropical distribution, which would apply to <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> in Hawai‘i and <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">guezei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> in the southwest Indian Ocean, but less so in light of the undescribed species in Palau. One potential explanation for such disjunct distributions is that these are relics of a once more widely distributed genus (paleoendemics; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Bellwood and Meyer 2009</xref>). Another, perhaps more likely explanation is that the dearth of mesophotic exploration across the tropical central and western Pacific and Indian Oceans has left significant gaps in our understanding of <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> distribution, and that additional populations and species await discovery.</p>
          <!--PageBreak-->
        </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>We are particularly grateful to Peter K. Basabe for enabling the collection of the first specimen of this species. E. H. "Deetsie" Chave was instrumental in the original discovery and documentation of this species. We also thank Roger Pfeffer, Joseph Dituri, John L. Earle, and Jennifer Williams for their respective roles in support of deep rebreather diving operations from 1998 through 2005 on which individuals of <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> were observed or collected. Kelly Gleason, Jason Leonard, Brian Hauk, Daniel Wagner, Keo Lopes, Stephen Matadobra, Hadley Owen, Louise Giuseffi, Elizabeth Kehn, Sarah Harris, and the officers and crew of <abbrev xlink:title="U.S. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration" id="ABBRID0EZ6AG">NOAA</abbrev> ship <italic>Hi‘ialakai</italic> assisted with <abbrev xlink:title="Northwestern Hawaiian Islands" id="ABBRID0ECABG">NWHI</abbrev> dive operations. Joshua M. Copus provided the DNA Barcodes and performed the genetic analysis. Greg McFall of the <abbrev xlink:title="U.S. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration" id="ABBRID0EKABG">NOAA</abbrev> Diving Center kindly allowed us to include his photo represented here as Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>. Brian W. Bowen, John E. Randall, Helen A. Randall, and <named-content xlink:type="simple" content-type="institution" xlink:href="http://grbio.org/institution/neal-l-evenhuis" id="NCID0EVABG">Neal L. Evenhuis</named-content> reviewed this manuscript and provided very helpful and constructive suggestions for improvement. Observations and collection of specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> off O‘ahu were supported by the Hawaii Undersea Research Laboratory, the Association for Marine Exploration, and funding from the <abbrev xlink:title="U.S. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration" id="ABBRID0EEBBG">NOAA</abbrev> Coral Reef Conservation Program research grants program administered by <abbrev content-type="institution" xlink:title="Hawaii Undersea Research Laboratory" id="ABBRID0ELBBG">HURL</abbrev> under award NA05OAR4301108 and NA09OAR4300219, project numbers HC07-11 and HC08-06. Observations and collection of specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basabei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> in the <abbrev xlink:title="Northwestern Hawaiian Islands" id="ABBRID0E1BBG">NWHI</abbrev> were funded by <abbrev xlink:title="U.S. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration" id="ABBRID0E5BBG">NOAA</abbrev>’s National Ocean Service, and taxonomic work was supported through a grant from the <abbrev xlink:title="U.S. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration" id="ABBRID0EFCBG">NOAA</abbrev> Papahānaumokuākea Marine National Monument to Bernice P. <named-content xlink:type="simple" content-type="institution" xlink:href="http://grbio.org/institution/bishop-museum" id="NCID0EMCBG">Bishop Museum</named-content>. Research was conducted under Papahānaumokuākea Marine National Monument permits PMNM-2009-38 and PMNM-2015-029 to Randall Kosaki. The scientific results and conclusions, as well as any views or opinions expressed herein, are those of the authors, and do not necessarily reflect the views of <abbrev xlink:title="U.S. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration" id="ABBRID0EWCBG">NOAA</abbrev> or the Department of Commerce. This publication does not constitute an endorsement of any commercial product or intend to be an opinion beyond scientific or other results obtained by <abbrev xlink:title="U.S. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration" id="ABBRID0E4CBG">NOAA</abbrev>. This work is Contribution No. 2016-015 to the Hawaii Biological Survey.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname> <given-names>GR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steene</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <source>A guide to Angelfishes and Butterflyfishes</source>. <publisher-name>Odyssey Publishing</publisher-name>, <size units="page">250 pp</size>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname> <given-names>EK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Puglise</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname> <given-names>PT</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Mesophotic coral ecosystems – A lifeboat for coral reefs?</article-title> <source>The United Nations Environment Programme and GRID-Arendal, Nairobi and Arendal</source>, <size units="page">98 pp</size>. <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://apps.unep.org/publications/pmtdocuments/-Mesophotic_Coral_Ecosystems__A_lifeboat_for_coral_reefs_-2016Mesoreport_finaldraft.pdf.pdf">http://apps.unep.org/publications/pmtdocuments/-Mesophotic_Coral_Ecosystems__A_lifeboat_for_coral_reefs_-2016Mesoreport_finaldraft.pdf.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bellwood</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname> <given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Searching for heat in a marine biodiversity hotspot.</article-title> <source>Journal of Biogeography</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>569</fpage>–<lpage>576</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/j.1365-2699.2008.02029.x">10.1111/j.1365-2699.2008.02029.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bellwood</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Herwerden</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Konow</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Evolution and biogeography of marine angelfishes (<tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Pisces</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="family">Pomacanthidae</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>).</article-title> <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>140</fpage>–<lpage>155</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.ympev.2004.04.015">10.1016/j.ympev.2004.04.015</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <!--PageBreak-->
      <ref id="B5">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowen</surname> <given-names>BW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bass</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rocha</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname> <given-names>WS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Phylogeography of the trumpetfish (<italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Aulostomus</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> spp.): ring species complex on a global scale.</article-title> <source>Evolution</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>1029</fpage>–<lpage>1039</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1554/0014-3820(2001)055[1029:POTTAR]2.0.CO;2">10.1554/0014-3820(2001)055[1029:POTTAR]2.0.CO;2</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Copus</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pyle</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Earle</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title><italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Neoniphon</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">pencei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>, a new species of holocentrid (<tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="subclass">Teleostei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="order">Beryciformes</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>) from Rarotonga, Cook Islands.</article-title> <source>Biodiversity Data Journal</source> <volume>3</volume>: <elocation-id>e4180</elocation-id>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3897/BDJ.3.e4180">10.3897/BDJ.3.e4180</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fessler</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Westneat</surname> <given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Molecular phylogenetics of the butterflyfishes (<tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="family">Chaetodontidae</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>): Taxonomy and biogeography of a global coral reef fish family.</article-title> <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>50</fpage>–<lpage>68</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.ympev.2007.05.018">10.1016/j.ympev.2007.05.018</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gill</surname> <given-names>TN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1862</year>) <article-title>Remarks on the relations of the genera and other groups of Cuban fishes.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>235</fpage>–<lpage>242</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Günther</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1860</year>) <source>Catalogue of the fishes in the British Museum. Catalogue of the acanthopterygian fishes in the collection of the British Museum. Squamipinnes, <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="family">Cirrhitidae</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="family">Triglidae</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="family">Trachinidae</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="family">Sciaenidae</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="family">Polynemidae</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="family">Sphyraenidae</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="family">Trichiuridae</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="family">Scombridae</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="family">Carangidae</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="family">Xiphiidae</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>.</source> <publisher-name>British Museum</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>London 2</publisher-loc>, <size units="page">548 pp</size>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hinderstein</surname> <given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marr</surname> <given-names>JCA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname> <given-names>FA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dowgiallo</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Puglise</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pyle</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zawada</surname> <given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Appeldoorn</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Mesophotic coral ecosystems: characterization, ecology, and management.</article-title> <source>Coral Reefs</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>247</fpage>–<lpage>251</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s00338-010-0614-5">10.1007/s00338-010-0614-5</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hourigan</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Environmental determinants of butterflyfish social systems.</article-title> <source>Environmental Biology of Fishes</source> <volume>25</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/BF00002201">10.1007/BF00002201</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jenkins</surname> <given-names>OP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1901</year>) <article-title>Descriptions of fifteen new species of fishes from the Hawaiian Islands.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the US Fish Commission</source> <volume>19</volume>(<issue>1899</issue>): <fpage>387</fpage>–<lpage>404</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Johns</surname> <given-names>GC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Avise</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>A comparative summary of genetic distances in the vertebrates from the mitochondrial cytochrome <italic>b</italic> gene.</article-title> <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1481</fpage>–<lpage>1490</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1093/oxfordjournals.molbev.a025875">10.1093/oxfordjournals.molbev.a025875</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jordan</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Evermann</surname> <given-names>BW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1903</year>) <article-title>Descriptions of new genera and species of fishes from the Hawaiian Islands.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the US Fish Commission</source> <volume>22</volume>(<issue>1902</issue>): <fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>208</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kane</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kosaki</surname> <given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>High levels of mesophotic reef fish endemism in the Northwestern Hawaiian Islands.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of Marine Science</source> <volume>90</volume>: <fpage>693</fpage>–<lpage>703</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.5343/bms.2013.1053">10.5343/bms.2013.1053</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kosaki</surname> <given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pyle</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leonard</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hauk</surname> <given-names>BB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitton</surname> <given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>100% endemism in mesophotic reef fish assemblages at Kure Atoll, Hawaiian Islands.</article-title> <source>Marine Biodiversity</source> <volume>2016</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>2</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s12526-016-0510-5">10.1007/s12526-016-0510-5</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Maugé</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauchot</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1976</year>) <article-title>Une espèce nouvelle de Chétodon de l’océan Indien occidental: <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Chaetodon</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">guezei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> (<tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Pisces</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name> : <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="family">Chaetodontidae</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>).</article-title> <source>Bulletin du Muséum National D ‘Histoire Naturelle</source> (<volume-series>3</volume-series>) <volume>355</volume>: <fpage>89</fpage>–<lpage>101</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nalbant</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> (<tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Pisces</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name> : <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="family">Chaetodontidae</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>) in eastern Pacific Ocean (Baja California – Galapagos) with discussion on the phylogeny of the group.</article-title> <source>Travaux du Muséum d’Histoire Naturelle ‘Grigore Antipa’</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>497</fpage>–<lpage>526</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Poey</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1860</year>) <source>Memorias sobra la historia natural de la Isla de Cuba, acompañadas de sumarios Latinos y extractos en Francés</source>. <volume>Tomo 2</volume>. <publisher-loc>La Habana</publisher-loc> <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>336</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B20">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pratchett</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berumen</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kapoor</surname> <given-names>BB</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) (<year>2013</year>) <source>Biology of Butterflyfishes.</source> <publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Boca Raton FL</publisher-loc>, <size units="page">352 pp</size>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <!--PageBreak-->
      <ref id="B21">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pyle</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Exploring deep coral reefs: How much coral reef biodiversity are we missing?</article-title> <source>Global Biodiversity</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B22">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pyle</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Assessing undiscovered fish biodiversity on deep coral reefs using advanced self-contained diving technology.</article-title> <source>Marine Technology Society Journal</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>82</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.4031/MTSJ.34.4.11">10.4031/MTSJ.34.4.11</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B23">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pyle</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chave</surname> <given-names>EH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>First record of the Chaetodontid Genus <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Prognathodes</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> from the Hawaiian Islands.</article-title> <source>Pacific Science</source> <volume>48</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>90</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>. <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/10125/2200">http://hdl.handle.net/10125/2200</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B24">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Randall</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lobel</surname> <given-names>PS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chave</surname> <given-names>EH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Annotated checklist of the fishes of Johnston Island.</article-title> <source>Pacific Science</source> <volume>39</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>24</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>. <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/10125/510">http://hdl.handle.net/10125/510</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B25">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Randall</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Reef and shore fishes of the Hawaiian Islands.</source> <publisher-name>University of Hawaii Sea Grant College Program</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Honolulu</publisher-loc>, <size units="page">546 pp</size>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B26">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Randall</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rocha</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title><italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Chaetodontoplus</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">poliourus</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>, A new angelfish (<tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="order">Perciformes</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="family">Pomacanthidae</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>) from the tropical western Atlantic.</article-title> <source>The Raffles Bulletin of Zoology</source> <volume>57</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>511</fpage>–<lpage>520</lpage>. <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lkcnhm.nus.edu.sg/nus/pdf/PUBLICATION/Raffles%20Bulletin%20of%20Zoology/Past%20Volumes/RBZ%2057(2)/57rbz511-520.pdf">http://lkcnhm.nus.edu.sg/nus/pdf/PUBLICATION/Raffles%20Bulletin%20of%20Zoology/Past%20Volumes/RBZ%2057(2)/57rbz511-520.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B27">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Reese</surname> <given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1975</year>) <article-title>A comparative study of the social behavior and related ecology of reef fishes of the family <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="family">Chaetodontidae</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>.</article-title> <source>Ethology</source> <volume>37</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/j.1439-0310.1975.tb01126.x">10.1111/j.1439-0310.1975.tb01126.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B28">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Reece</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowen</surname> <given-names>BW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larson</surname> <given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Molecular phylogenetics of moray eels (<tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="family">Muraenidae</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>) demonstrates multiple origins of a shell-crushing jaw (<italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Gymnomuraena</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Echidna</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>) and multiple colonizations of the Atlantic Ocean.</article-title> <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>829</fpage>–<lpage>835</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.ympev.2010.07.013">10.1016/j.ympev.2010.07.013</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B29">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rocha</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Mitochondrial DNA and color pattern variation in three western Atlantic <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Halichoeres</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> (<tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="family">Labridae</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>), with the revalidation of two species.</article-title> <source>Copeia</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>770</fpage>–<lpage>782</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1643/CG-04-106">10.1643/CG-04-106</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B30">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rocha</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindeman</surname> <given-names>KC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rocha</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lessios</surname> <given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Historical biogeography and speciation in the reef fish genus <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Haemulon</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> (<tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="subclass">Teleostei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="family">Haemulidae</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>).</article-title> <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</source> <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>91</fpage>–<lpage>928</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.ympev.2008.05.024">10.1016/j.ympev.2008.05.024</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B31">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>WL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Webb</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blum</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The evolution of the laterophysic connection with a revised phylogeny and taxonomy of butterflyfishes (<tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="subclass">Teleostei</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="family">Chaetodontidae</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>).</article-title> <source>Cladistics</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>287</fpage>–<lpage>306</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/j.1096-0031.2003.tb00374.x">10.1111/j.1096-0031.2003.tb00374.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B32">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>TenBruggencate</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Unknown fish swims into sight.</article-title> <source>The Honolulu Advertiser</source>, <conf-date>June 10, 1998</conf-date>, <issue>A-1</issue>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B33">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kosaki</surname> <given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spalding</surname> <given-names>HL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitton</surname> <given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pyle</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sherwood</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsuda</surname> <given-names>RT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calcinai</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Mesophotic surveys of the flora and fauna at Johnston Atoll, Central Pacific Ocean.</article-title> <source>Marine Biodiversity Records</source> <year>2014</year>: <volume>7</volume>: <elocation-id>e68</elocation-id>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1017/S1755267214000785">10.1017/S1755267214000785</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B34">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yabuta</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berumen</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Social structure and spawning behavior of <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Chaetodon</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> butterflyfishes.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pratchett</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berumen</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kapoor</surname> <given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Biology of Butterflyfishes</source>. <publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Boca Raton</publisher-loc>, <fpage>200</fpage>–<lpage>225</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1201/b15458-9">10.1201/b15458-9</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
