<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.618.8886</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A note on captive breeding and reproductive parameters of the Chinese pangolin, <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Manis</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">pentadactyla</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> Linnaeus, 1758</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Fuhua</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>Shibao</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Zou</surname>
            <given-names>Cuiyun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Qiaoyun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Shaoshan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>Ruyong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>School of Life Science, South China Normal University, Guangzhou 510631, P. R. China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="corresp">
          <p>Corresponding author: Shibao Wu (<email xlink:type="simple">wushibao@163.com</email>)</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="edited-by">
          <p>Academic editor: P. Stoev</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>19</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <issue>618</issue>
      <fpage>129</fpage>
      <lpage>144</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>29</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Fuhua Zhang, Shibao Wu, Cuiyun Zou, Qiaoyun Wang, Shaoshan Li, Ruyong Sun</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0" xlink:type="simple">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY 4.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri content-type="zoobank" xlink:type="simple">http://zoobank.org/3EC354B3-C669-4C96-A82C-4015ED231DCD</self-uri>
      <abstract>
        <label>Abstract</label>
        <p>The Chinese pangolin (<italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Manis</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">pentadactyla</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> Linnaeus, 1758) is a critically endangered species, and documents on its captive breeding and reproductive parameters are scarce. MP8, kept in the Pangolin Research Base for Artificial Rescue and Conservation Breeding of South China Normal University (the PRB-SCNU), gave birth to a male offspring (MP86) on 19 October 2011. The baby pangolin was well developed, with a weight of 120 g and a total length of 23.2 cm. The gestation length of MP8 was estimated to be from 182 to 225d. Reproductive parameters of the Chinese pangolin are discussed based on collected data about this species. The Chinese pangolin has an obvious reproductive seasonality and its gestation length is typically six to seven months. In this observation, estrus and mating principally occurred in a one-year period from February to July. Parturition principally took place from September to February of the next year. Chinese pangolins usually give birth to one offspring at a time (n = 27). Sex ratio at birth was 0.71:1 (♀:♂, n = 12). Average weight for the reproducible females was 3.57 ± 1.38 kg (2.14–6.8 kg, n = 15). We estimated that Chinese pangolins could reach sexual maturity before they were one year old.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <label>Keywords</label>
        <kwd>Age of sexual maturity</kwd>
        <kwd>birth record</kwd>
        <kwd>breeding season</kwd>
        <kwd>gestation period</kwd>
        <kwd>parturition</kwd>
        <kwd><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="order">Pholidota</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></kwd>
        <!--PageBreak-->
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
    <notes>
      <sec sec-type="Citation" id="SECID0ETF">
        <title>Citation</title>
        <p>Zhang F, Wu S, Zou C, Wang Q, Li S, Sun R (2016) A note on captive breeding and reproductive parameters of the Chinese pangolin, <italic>Manis pentadactyla</italic> Linnaeus, 1758. ZooKeys 618: 129–144. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3897/zookeys.618.8886">10.3897/zookeys.618.8886</ext-link></p>
      </sec>
    </notes>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="Introduction" id="SECID0EAG">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The Chinese pangolin (<italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Manis</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">pentadactyla</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> Linnaeus, 1758) belonging to the order <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="order">Pholidota</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name> of <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="class">Mammalia</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name> is one of eight extant species of pangolins around the world (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Gaubert and Antunes 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Wu et al. 2004a</xref>), and mainly distributes in the southern area of the Yangtze River, China (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Wu et al. 2005</xref>). Due to its high value for medicine and food, a high proportion of the population has been illegally hunted and traded. Moreover, its habitats has also been heavily destroyed, thus the population has declined sharply in recent years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Wu et al. 2004b</xref>). In 2014, the Chinese pangolin was assessed as critically endangered by IUCN (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Challender et al. 2014</xref>). Keeping critically endangered species in artificial facilities is <italic>ex-situ</italic> conservation – a temporary measure for urgently saving these species from wild. Chinese pangolins were first maintained in captivity in 1877; and afterwards, at least twenty-four zoos and five universities and institutions tried to keep them. In these practices, however, most of the captive pangolin individuals died within one year (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Chao et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Cheng et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Chin et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Clark et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Gu et al. 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Heath and Vanderlip 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Hoyt 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Masui 1967</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Shi and Wang 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Wang 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">Wilson 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Wu 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Yang et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">2007</xref>). Even fewer reproductive records about the female Chinese pangolins’ rutting, mating, pregnancy rate, and births in captivity have been reported. So far, only four cases, three in Taipei Zoo and one at the Research Institute of Forestry of Gaoan County in Jiangxi Province, China, have been made available for study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Chin et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Shi and Wang 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Yang et al. 2007</xref>).</p>
      <p>Reproductive parameters, such as age of sexual maturity, breeding season, gestation period, litter size, and sex ratio at birth are basic data for the scientific management of wildlife populations and the prediction of future trends. They are also fundamental for making plans for the captive breeding of pangolins. However, reproductive parameters of the Chinese pangolin are fragmentary, and presented in few studies; data have been mainly based on talking with hunters, dissecting dead pregnant pangolins, and noting rescued pregnant pangolins that gave birth in captivity. Additionally, most of these parameters have been presented as a range, which is not accurate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Chao et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Cheng et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Heath and Vanderlip 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Liu and Xu 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Luo et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Masui 1967</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Ogilvie and Bridgwater 1967</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Wang 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Wu 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Zhu-Ge and Huang 1989</xref>). Data from direct observations in captivity are unusually scarce (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Chin et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Shi and Wang 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Yang et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">2007</xref>). Length of the gestation period of the Chinese pangolin in the Taipei Zoo has varied considerably. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Yang et al. (2007)</xref> suggested the gestation period was less than 169d, however, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Chin et al. (2011)</xref> thought that it might be from 318 to 372d. Further research on reproductive parameters of the Chinese pangolin is needed, with more direct observations taken.</p>
      <p>In June, 2010, the Pangolin Research Base for Artificial Rescue and Conservation Breeding of South China Normal University (the PRB-SCNU) was built in the village of Sima, in the town of Changping, in the city of Dongguan. There, studies on rescu<!--PageBreak-->ing and keeping pangolins in captivity were conducted. From then until now, one Chinese pangolin and eight Sunda pangolins (<italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Manis</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">javanica</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> Desmarest, 1822) have conceived and given birth to offspring in captivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Zhang et al. 2015</xref>). The information on captive breeding of the Chinese pangolin reported in this paper is intended to enrich the reproductive knowledge and the direct observations of the reproductive parameters of this species. By combining data in this note with existing reproductive data about the Chinese pangolin, the reproductive parameters of this species was discussed in the present paper, findings in this study will then provide guidance for selecting individuals to be mated, determining the season for mating, predicting the parturition time, and creating breeding plans. Data are intended to provide benefits to the management of captive Chinese pangolins, and provide further information for enhancing management practices and predicting population trends of the wild population.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="SECID0EJEAC">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec sec-type="Subjects" id="SECID0ENEAC">
        <title>Subjects</title>
        <p>Subjects of this study were two wild-born Chinese pangolins marked as MP1 (♂) and MP8 (♀) who were sent to the PRB-SCNU on 24 June and 16 July 2010, respectively. When they arrived, their weights were measured (2.5 kg for MP1 and 3.3 kg for MP8). They were individually housed. Pangolins received treatment for all apparent parasites and disease, adjusted to domestic feeding habits, and adapted to the captive environment.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="Housing" id="SECID0ESEAC">
        <title>Housing</title>
        <p>Housing details for the two Chinese pangolins were the same as housing the Sunda pangolin at PRB-SCNU that have been described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Zhang et al. (2015)</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="Housing together and mating" id="SECID0E3EAC">
        <title>Housing together and mating</title>
        <p>The female MP8 and the male MP1 were housed together during the period from 8 March to 20 April 2011. After that, MP8 was housed individually until she gave birth to a baby pangolin. After their separation, we observed the breasts of MP8 to be enlarged, with a little secretion on her papilla. Accordingly, we suspected that MP8 was pregnant, which was proved true several months later by a baby pangolin birth. Undoubtedly, MP8 mated with MP1 during the period in which they were housed together. Unfortunately, we missed observing their mating behavior so we cannot determine the exact mating date.</p>
        <!--PageBreak-->
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="Results" id="SECID0ECFAC">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec sec-type="Gestation length and number of offspring" id="SECID0EGFAC">
        <title>Gestation length and number of offspring</title>
        <p>The keeper found a dead pangolin baby (MP86) whose umbilical cord (with a length of 9.2 cm) was still connected to the placenta. The baby was buried in the sandy soil substrates of the nest and under a brick. Examining MP8, we observed breast swelling, indicating her breasts were full of milk. In addition, her vulvae displayed redness with some red viscous secretion. She was sensitive to sound, and in response to noise, became quite alert. When we got close to her, she made a sound of “fu~fu~” and curled herself tightly. Undoubtedly, she was showing strong epimeletic behavior after parturition. When the keeper checked her nest at about 0 o’clock on 19 October, he did not observe MP8 showing any sign of approaching parturition. So MP86 was likely born between 0:00 and 8:00 am of 19 October. Considering MP8 and MP1 were housed together between 8 March and 20 April, the gestation length of MP8 was estimated to be from 182 to 225d. The number of offspring was one.</p>
        <p>When the keeper checked the nest of MP8 on the morning of 19 October at approximately 8:00 am, he also found that her bowls for food and water had changed position and had fallen over. Approximately 30 g of artificial food remained in her food bowl. The sandy soil substrate of her enclosure was freshly turned, so we suspected that around the time of delivery MP8 showed several abnormal behaviors with dysphoric emotion.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="Changes of morphology and weight for MP8" id="SECID0EMFAC">
        <title>Changes of morphology and weight for MP8</title>
        <p>During the pregnancy, MP8 did not show any significant morphological changes except for enlarged breasts and concurrent weight gain. Before the pangolins were housed together, her two breasts were only small bumps with a height less than 0.3 cm, with a diameter at the base of the breast of 0.5 cm. Her nipples were not obvious either. After being housed together, the female’s breasts were first observed to be swollen on 24 April 2011; the nipples began to distend outward with some waxy secretion on their surfaces. Her breasts and nipples enlarged gradually, with the breasts becoming significantly fuller and more upright. At the same time, secretions also became thicker. Before her parturition, her breasts had a height of 1.5 cm with a diameter at the base of the breast of 1.1 cm (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Swollen breasts and waxy secretions have also been noted in other reports (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Heath and Vanderlip 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Yang et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">2007</xref>). During the gestation period, MP8’s daily intake for food increased from 50 g to 70 g and her weight increased from 5.0 to 6.55 kg – an increase of 31% (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Breast and waxy secretion covering the nipple surface of the female pangolin MP8 for the parturition the day before (by Fuhua Zhang, 18 Oct 2011). <bold>a</bold> breast <bold>b</bold> nipple <bold>c</bold> waxy secretion covering the nipple surface.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="zookeys-618-e8886-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="oo_103648.jpg"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 2.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Body weight change of the female pangolin MP8 during the gestation period (from 8 Mar to 19 Oct 2011). <bold>A</bold> duration for MP8 housing with MP1 together <bold>B</bold> date of MP8 giving birth.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="zookeys-618-e8886-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="oo_103649.jpg"/>
        </fig>
        <!--PageBreak-->
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="Morphological features of MP86" id="SECID0ELHAC">
        <title>Morphological features of MP86</title>
        <p>After clearing the sand on its surface, the skin of the head and abdomen of MP86 were found to be broken. It was a male pangolin with its head, limbs, claws, and tail well developed.</p>
        <p>Its extraoral tongue extended 2.6 cm. Overlapping scales covered its body, with most closely tied to its surface. Scales tied to the surface were soft and not cuticularized; free parts of the scales were narrow, with a length of about 1 to 2 mm. The scales were grey, and at the base much darker; free parts were milky white, transparent, and membranous (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Delicate and milky white hair was found among some scales.</p>
        <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 3.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>The newborn Chinese pangolin baby MP86 (by Fuhua Zhang, 19 Oct 2011).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="zookeys-618-e8886-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="oo_103650.jpg"/>
        </fig>
        <!--PageBreak-->
        <p>Its claws were bent and sharp. Their ends were wrapped in soft ivory skin membrane. This membrane structure may be related to preventing the baby’s claws from scratching the dam’s vagina during its transit through the birth canal. Its abdomen was naked, without any scales. Morphological index data are presented in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>. According to the degree of MP86’s development and Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>, we concluded it had been mature and reached full term. MP86 was the offspring of natural childbirth.</p>
        <table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Table 1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Measurements of the morphological indexes for the baby MP86.</p>
          </caption>
          <table id="TID0EXPAG" rules="all">
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Items</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outcome</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body mass</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120 g</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of head and body</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.6 cm</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tail length</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6 cm</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total length</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.2 cm</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Head length</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6 cm</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of the middle claw of fore limb</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7 cm</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of the middle claw of hind limb</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8 cm</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ear length</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 cm</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of rows of scales around middle of the body</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of rows of ridge scales on one side of the body</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of the scales on the edge of one side of the tail</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exposed tongue length</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6 cm</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
        <!--PageBreak-->
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="Discussion" id="SECID0EVLAC">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Data from a total of twenty Chinese pangolin births were collected, with five from captive breeding (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). MP86, reported in this paper, was the fifth Chinese pangolin baby in the world to be bred in captivity (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). The Chinese pangolin remains critically endangered, and it is difficult to get samples in the wild. Data from captive breeding records and reproductive parameters of the species in this study are valuable, as information collected enriches our understanding of the reproductive biology and ecology of this critically endangered species.</p>
      <table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        <label>Table 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>The parturition records and estimated gestation period of Chinese pangolins.</p>
        </caption>
        <table id="TID0ECVAG" rules="all">
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <th rowspan="2" colspan="1">No.</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="7">Mothers</th>
              <th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Litter size</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="4">New born babies</th>
              <th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Source</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ID</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arrival Data (<abbrev xlink:title="Body weight" id="ABBRID0EHNAC">BW</abbrev>, g)</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mating Date (<abbrev xlink:title="Body weight" id="ABBRID0E1NAC">BW</abbrev>, g)</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mating sites</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Giving birth date (<abbrev xlink:title="Body weight" id="ABBRID0EQOAC">BW</abbrev>, g)</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Giving birth<break/> sites</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gestation length (d)</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <abbrev xlink:title="Body weight" id="ABBRID0EOPAC">BW</abbrev>
                <break/> (g)</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <abbrev xlink:title="Total length" id="ABBRID0ECAAE">TL</abbrev>
                <break/> (cm)</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Condition</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3#</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 Mar 1984 (3850)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1–30 Jun 1984 (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Captive</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 Jan 1985 (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gaoan Forestry<break/> Institute</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">187–216</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">165</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Shi and Wang 1985</xref>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1#</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 Nov 1984 (2350)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <abbrev xlink:title="Before" id="ABBRID0EPCAE">Bef</abbrev> 4 Nov 1984 (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 Feb 1985 (3000)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">University of California</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;93</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Viable</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Heath and Vanderlip 1988</xref>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">‡</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 Nov 1995<sup>†</sup> (3855)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <abbrev xlink:title="Before" id="ABBRID0EXEAE">Bef</abbrev> 6 Nov 1995 (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 Feb 1996 (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xiashan Rare Animals Farm</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;101</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.5</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stillborn</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Wu 1998</xref>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">‡</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">? (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">? (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 Feb 1993 (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taipei Zoo</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stillborn</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Yang et al. 2001</xref>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">‡</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 Dec 1991<sup>†</sup> (4000)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <abbrev xlink:title="Before" id="ABBRID0EPIAE">Bef</abbrev> 21 Dec 1991 (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 Feb 1992 (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taiwan Forestry Institute</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;68</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.2</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stillborn</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Chao et al. 1993</xref>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">‡</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">? 1966 (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">? (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">? Aug 1966 (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rochester Zoo</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Viable</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Ogilvie and Bridgwater 1967</xref>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 Nov 2005 (2800)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <abbrev xlink:title="Before" id="ABBRID0EEMAE">Bef</abbrev> 7 Nov 2005 (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 Sep 2006 (1850)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taipei Zoo</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;318</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stillborn</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Chin et al. 2011</xref>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">‡</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">? Sep 2015<sup>†</sup></td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">? (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 Sep 2015</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hunter’s home</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.5</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Viable</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interview hunter</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">‡</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">? (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">? (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">? Oct ? (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Viable</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Liu and Xu 1981</xref>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 Oct 2006 (2140)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <abbrev xlink:title="Before" id="ABBRID0EGRAE">Bef</abbrev> 2 Oct 2006 (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 Oct 2007 (4780)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taipei Zoo</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;372</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Viable</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Chin et al. 2011</xref>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MP8</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 Jul 2010 (3300)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 Mar – 20 Apr 2011 (5000)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Captive</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 Oct 2011 (6300)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PRB-SCNU</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">182–225</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.2</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">this study</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">‡</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">? (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">? (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 Nov 2010 (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PRB-SCNU</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.5</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Viable</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PRB-SCNU</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 Jul 2005 (2280)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23–27 Dec 2005 (3600)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Captive</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 Nov 2006 (6050)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taipei Zoo</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">317–321</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Viable</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Chin et al. 2011</xref>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3#</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 Nov 1984 (2950)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <abbrev xlink:title="Before" id="ABBRID0ERXAE">Bef</abbrev> 4 Nov 1984 (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 Nov 1984 (3000)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">University of California</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;10</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Viable</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Heath and Vanderlip 1988</xref>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">‡</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 Mar 1998 (3000)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 Jun - ? 1998 (3100)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Captive</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 Nov 1998 (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taipei Zoo</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≤166</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Viable</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Yang et al. 2001</xref>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">‡</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">? (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">? (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">? Dec 1978 (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Viable</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Liu and Xu 1981</xref>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">‡</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 May 1996 (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">? (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Captive</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 Dec 1997 (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taipei Zoo</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Viable</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Yang et al. 2001</xref>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">‡</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 Dec 1965 (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <abbrev xlink:title="Before" id="ABBRID0EG5AE">Bef</abbrev> 9 Dec 1965 (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 Dec 1965 (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ueno Zoo</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;16</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Viable</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Masui 1967</xref>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">‡</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">? Nov 2014<sup>†</sup> (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">? (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">? Nov 2014 (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Viable</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interview hunter</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">‡</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">? (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">? (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1986 or 1987 (?)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taipei Zoo</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Hoyt 1987</xref>
              </td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn>
            <p>† = wild-caught date; ? = Unknown; ‡ = No ID Number; <abbrev id="ABBRID0EBDAG">Bef<def><p> = Before</p></def></abbrev>; <abbrev id="ABBRID0E1DAG">BW<def><p> = Body weight</p></def></abbrev>; <abbrev id="ABBRID0ENEAG">TL<def><p> = Total length</p></def></abbrev>.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <sec sec-type="Weight change of the pregnant pangolins and survival of the newborns" id="SECID0E1EAG">
        <title>Weight change of the pregnant pangolins and survival of the newborns</title>
        <p>During pregnancy, the weight of MP8 increased by 31% (1.55 kg) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). It has been suggested that weight increase in pregnant pangolins before delivery would improve the survival rate of newborn infants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Bagatto et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Dehnhard et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Heath 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Heath and Hammel 1986</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Chin et al. (2011)</xref> reported that the weight of two young pregnant Chinese pangolins increased by 63.89% (from 3.6 kg to 6.05 kg) and 134.0% (from 2.14 kg to 4.78 kg), respectively, before they gave birth to babies. At birth, these babies weighed 80 g and 110 g, respectively, and this modest increase in weight indicates good nutritional status of the mothers, and is helpful for the development of fetuses and births of healthy cubs. Weight gain also contributes to meeting the nutritional need of postpartum lactation so the fetus can survive more easily, unlike a decrease in weight, which would restrict the survival of the cubs or even cause stillbirth. A female Chinese pangolin whose weight decreased by 950 g (from 2.8 kg to 1.85 kg) gave birth to a cub with a weight of 52 g, who died within a few minutes after its birth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Chin et al. 2011</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="Development and health of the newborn pangolins" id="SECID0E3FAG">
        <title>Development and health of the newborn pangolins</title>
        <p>Twenty birth records of Chinese pangolins have been counted in this paper (see Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Descriptions of the babies were similar. The average weight of baby pangolins was 103.92 ± 37.40 g (52–180 g, n = 12); Total length was 21.86 ± 2.98 cm (18.5–26.5 cm, n = 7). The weight of newborn baby pangolins has been suggested as an assessment criterion for the successful reproduction of Chinese pangolins, as cubs with higher weights usually survive easily (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Chin et al. 2011</xref>). Among the thirteen viable cubs in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>, seven had known weights (No. 2, No. 8, No. 10, No. 12, No. 13, No. 14, No. 16) and were relatively big, with weights over 80 g (the largest was 180 g). Four were stillborn without any vital signs. Three of these had known weights (from 52 to 75 g). They were relatively small and weakly developed. To further describe the degree of development in the newborn Chinese pangolins, we tried to use DI, an index of fatter and thinner, which represents a ratio of the fetus’ weight to its total length. The <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->DIs of the four surviving baby pangolins (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>: No. 2, No. 8, No. 12, No. 14) were 4.38, 4.49, 4.65, and 6.79, all of which exceeded 4.2. The DIs of the two dead animals (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>: No. 3, No. 5) were 3.65 and 4.05, so below 4.2. We suggest a weight of 80 g and a DI of 4.2 could be used as the scale to describe the degree of development in newborn Chinese pangolins. Of course, more samples are needed to confirm this idea.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="Gestation length" id="SECID0EZGAG">
        <title>Gestation length</title>
        <p>The gestation length of the Chinese pangolin was calculated based on direct observations and published data (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). It seemed that gestation length is not very clear and more data is needed, especially for those collected in captivity. In the present study, the gestation period was from 182 to 225d, in agreement with findings reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Shi and Wang (1985)</xref> (187–216d). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Yang et al. (2007)</xref> reported a gestation length of less than 169d, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Wang (1990)</xref> argued for a period of about eight months (240 d). However, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Chin et al. (2011)</xref> also reported the gestation length of three Chinese pangolins (A, B, and C) to be 317–321d, &gt; 318 d, and &gt;372 d, respectively (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>), all of which were over 300d, the results have large differences from that of the others. The gestation lengths of the Indian pangolin (<italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Manis</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">crassicaudata</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> Gray, 1827), Sunda pangolin, and Cape pangolin (<italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Manis</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">temminckii</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> Smuts, 1832) were about 165d, 180d, and 139d, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Panda et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Zhang et al. 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Van Ee 1966</xref>), all of which were less than 300d. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Wang et al. (1984)</xref> reported the gestation length of ninety-seven species of mammals which belonging to thirteen orders. Only a few large-sized species had gestation periods of over 300d, for example, Asian elephants (<italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Elephas</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">maximas</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>), Asian rhinoceros (<italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Rhinoceros</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">unicornis</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>), and bactrian camel (<italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Camelus</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">bactrianus</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>). Small animals tend to have shorter gestation lengths. Perhaps <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Chin et al. (2011)</xref> overestimated the gestation of the three Chinese pangolins (A, B, C).</p>
        <p>The gestation period is usually stable as it is genetically controlled (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Liu and Zheng 1997</xref>). But the gestation period of a few mammals may show larger fluctuations, such as that of the giant panda, whose gestation lengths have been noted as 140.3 ± 20.5d (from 89 to 186d)) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">Zhang and Wei 2006</xref>). Environmental conditions, health and nutritional status of the mother, delayed implantation, and reproductive hormone levels may each affect animals’ pregnancy lengths (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Silk 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Yang 2010</xref>). The three Chinese pangolins reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Chin et al. (2011)</xref> were kept in very narrow space (1.2×1.2×0.8 m). Thus, the relatively long gestation length of the three Chinese pangolins (A, B, and C) may be related to the disturbance of hormones caused by environmental stress.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="Mating and parturition season" id="SECID0ETKAG">
        <title>Mating and parturition season</title>
        <p>It is usually suggested that the Chinese pangolin has a specific mating and parturition season. Mating behavior has been mainly observed to occur in summer and seldom occurs in April and May or early autumn; births have mainly taken place in winter <!--PageBreak-->(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Heath 1992a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Liu and Xu 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Luo et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Wang 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Wu 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Zhu-Ge and Huang 1989</xref>). However, according to the descriptions of thirty-one interviewed hunters, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Chao et al. (1993)</xref> stated the Chinese pangolins mainly give birth to infants in the spring, between March and May, with the parturition season also later.</p>
        <p>In this study, a total of three female Chinese pangolins’ mating times were collected (No. 1, No. 11, and No. 13 in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Mating for No. 11 and No. 1 occurred between March and May and in June, respectively. Additional mating times for two pregnant pangolins (No. 2 and No. 3) were also estimated according to the times of their death and the degrees of development of embryos in the uterus. Their mating seemed to occur between February and March and between June and July, respectively (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). These few instances appear to show the mating season of the Chinese pangolins mainly occurred between February and July.</p>
        <table-wrap id="T3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Table 3.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Records of dissection and estimated mating time of the dead pregnant Chinese pangolins.</p>
          </caption>
          <table id="TID0EA6BG" rules="all">
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mother ID</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arrival date</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimated mating time</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mating site</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Died date</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Litter size</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Embryo/fetus mass (g)</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fetus gender</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">†</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">? Jan 1982</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Wang 1990</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FS3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 Mar 2011</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb or Mar 2011</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 Mar 2011</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PRB-SCNU</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MP7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 Jul 2010</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jun or Jul 2010</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 Jul 2010</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PRB-SCNU</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">†</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">? Sep 1978</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Liu and Xu 1981</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">†</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">? Oct 1979</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Liu and Xu 1981</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">†</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 Nov 2013</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 Nov 2013</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PRB-SCNU</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96004</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 Oct 1996</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 Nov 1996</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">108.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Cheng et al. 2000</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>† = No ID Number; ? = Unknown</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>Among the twenty birth records of Chinese pangolins gathered in this study, nineteen of their birth months were known, usually occurring from October to February of the next year, i.e., in autumn and winter (eighteen cases, accounting for a percentage of 94.7%) with a few occurring in August (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). This finding suggests the breeding season of Chinese pangolin is similar to that of the Cape pangolin, but different from the Sunda and Indian pangolins. Regarding the Cape pangolin, mating occurred from late summer to early autumn (between March and May in the southern hemisphere), with the birthing season in winter (from June to September in the southern hemisphere) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Heath 1992b</xref>); for Sunda and Indian pangolins, births have also been observed throughout the year (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Heath 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Mohapatra and Panda 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Zhang et al. 2015</xref>). Given that direct observations of the mating and parturition for the Chinese pangolin were few, more direct observations and documentation are necessary.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="Litter size and sex ratio at birth" id="SECID0ESVAG">
        <title>Litter size and sex ratio at birth</title>
        <p>It is commonly suggested that the Chinese pangolin give birth to one offspring at a time. In the current study, MP8 was observed to give birth to a single offspring, coinciding with other breeding records collected (n = 19) in the current study. This is in line with findings from our dissection of seven pregnant Chinese pangolins, where only one fetus was found in each uterus (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). This agrees with birth records for other pangolin species – the Sunda pangolin, Indian pangolin, Cape pangolin, and tree pangolin – where usually a single young was produced (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Hoyt 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Israel et al. 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Menzies 1967</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Mohapatra and Panda 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Van Ee 1966</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Zhang et al. 2015</xref>). However, for the Chinese pangolin and Indian pangolin, it is also stated that two baby pangolins can be born at the same time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Liu and Xu 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Wang 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Prater 2005</xref>). In August 2015, we visited China’s Xishuangbanna Natural Reserve, located in Yunnan Province, and interviewed several staff. Interviewees Li Xiaokun (on the staff of this nature reserve) and Lv Xinghua (from Ninger county, Yunnan province) told us that in 1979, they dug out an adult female pangolin and four similar-sized babies (approximately 1.0 kg) in a burrow with a depth of 1 meter in the Wulu River Forest <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->Farm in Mengwang Town, Jinghong City, Yunnan Province. This may indicate that the Chinese pangolin could give birth to four babies at a time.</p>
        <p>Sex ratio at birth of the Chinese pangolin has not been reported in other literature. A total of twelve newborn cubs whose gender were recorded in this paper (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>), including five females and seven males, suggests a sex ratio of 0.71:1 (♀:♂, n = 12). Female individuals were fewer than males, but this might be ascribed to the small sample size. Natural selection may force parents to regulate the sex ratio of their offspring according to parental ability to invest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Trivers and Willard 1973</xref>). Dams in good health have higher levels of investment and tend to give birth to more male cubs. A higher percentage of males mean females have more opportunities to select an excellent mate. This benefits the health of a population and prevents their decline and extinction. It must be kept in mind, however, that a greater number of males will consume more resources, thereby affecting the development of the population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Lumley et al. 2015</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="Weight of the pregnant and puerperal pangolins and age at sexual maturity" id="SECID0ERXAG">
        <title>Weight of the pregnant and puerperal pangolins and age at sexual maturity</title>
        <p>The age of sexual maturity for the Chinese pangolin remains unclear. Weights of fifteen sexually mature female Chinese pangolins were recorded in the present study (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>), however, it is unclear whether those pangolins were primiparous. Their average weight was 3.57 ± 1.39 kg, with a range of 2.14–6.8 kg (n = 15). Eight females, whose weights were between 2–3 kg, gave birth to offspring, accounting for 53.3% of the total. The <!--PageBreak-->weight of the smallest mother pangolin was only 2.14 kg. It has been reported that the six-month-old baby Chinese pangolin could attain a weight of 1.2–2.0 kg (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Liu and Xu 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Yang et al. 2001</xref>), or more (2.7 kg) (Masui, 1967). This indicates that the female Chinese pangolin could reproduce when she was approximately six months old. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Chin et al. (2011)</xref> argue that the Chinese pangolin could breed before the age of 1–1.5 year, which is in agreement with our conclusion. Sunda pangolins with average weights of 3.49 ± 0.90 kg (1.75–5.54 kg, n = 24) were confirmed to be pregnant, and reached sexual maturity at six to seven months old (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Zhang et al. 2015</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="T4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Table 4.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Weight of the collected female Chinese pangolins which have the ability to reproduce in this paper.</p>
          </caption>
          <table id="TID0ENLAI" rules="all">
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ID of the female</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body weight (kg)</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source</th>
                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Note</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Chin et al. 2011</xref>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pregnant</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">†</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Liu and Xu 1981</xref>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pregnant</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.35</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Heath and Hammel 1986</xref>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pregnant</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MP7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.42</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PRB-SCNU</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pregnant</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">†</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Liu and Xu 1981</xref>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">lactation</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.80</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Chin et al. 2011</xref>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pregnant</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.95</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Heath and Hammel 1986</xref>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pregnant</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">†</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Yang et al. 2001</xref>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">lactation</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Chin et al. 2011</xref>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">When mating</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">†</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.855</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Wu 1998</xref>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pregnant</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">†</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Chao et al. 1993</xref>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pregnant</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FS3</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PRB-SCNU</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pregnant</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MP8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.17</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PRB-SCNU</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">When mating</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">†</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interview hunter</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">lactation</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">†</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Yang et al. 2001</xref>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pregnant</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>† = No ID number.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="Conclusions" id="SECID0ETCBG">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <list list-type="order">
        <list-item>
          <p>There is an obvious breeding season for the Chinese pangolin: estrus and mating principally occurred from February to July in a one-year period, and parturition principally took place from September to February of the next year. The gestation length is typically six to seven months.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>Female Chinese pangolins may reach sexual maturity before one year old, even as early as six months old, or when their body weights reach over two kilograms.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>During the pregnancy, the Chinese pangolin does not show significant morphological changes except for its breast and body weight.</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>The Chinese pangolin usually gives birth to one offspring at a time. The body weight of all the surviving newborn babies was more than 80 g.</p>
        </list-item>
      </list>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>We would like to thank all those who work at the Pangolin Research Base for Artificial Rescue and Conservation Breeding of South China Normal University (the PRB-SCNU). We would further like to acknowledge and thank the Wildlife Rescue Center of Guangdong Province for providing the animals for this study. This research was supported by the Natural Science Foundation of Guangdong Province (No. S2013010013356), the Special Fund for Significant Science and Technology in Social Development Field of Guangdong Province (No. 2011A030100012), and the National Natural Science Foundation of China (31572286). We are also grateful to Prof. Martha Schirn (U.S.) and Dr. Zaiwang Zhang (Binzhou University) for reading through and checking the manuscript to correct the grammatical and semantic errors.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bagatto</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>CrossleyII</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burggren</surname> <given-names>WW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Physiological variability in neonatal armadillo quadruplets: within-and between-litter differences.</article-title> <source>Journal of Experimental Biology</source> <volume>203</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>1733</fpage>–<lpage>1740</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <!--PageBreak-->
      <ref id="B2">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Challender</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baillie</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ades</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaspal</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khatiwada</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chin</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>KC</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nash</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsieh</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title><italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Manis</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">pentadactyla</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>.</article-title> <source>The IUCN Red List of Threatened Species</source>. <comment>Version 2015.1</comment>. <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iucnredlist.org">www.iucnredlist.org</ext-link> [<date-in-citation content-type="download-date">Downloaded on 04 June 201</date-in-citation>]</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chao</surname> <given-names>JT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>YM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeh</surname> <given-names>WC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname> <given-names>KY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Notes on a newborn Formosan pangolin, <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Manis</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">pentadactyla</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="subspecies">pentadactyla</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>.</article-title> <source>Taiwan Museum</source> <volume>46</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname> <given-names>DY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>QS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname> <given-names>ZB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>ZC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Discussion on birth time of pangolins.</article-title> <source>Resource Development and Market</source> <volume>16</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <lpage>287</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chin</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lien</surname> <given-names>CY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname> <given-names>YT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>YC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeh</surname> <given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Monitoring the gestation period of rescued Formosan pangolin (<italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Manis</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">pentadactyla</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>) with progesterone radioimmunoassay.</article-title> <source>Zoo Biology</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thai</surname> <given-names>NV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phuong</surname> <given-names>TQ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A long way from home: the health status of Asian pangolins confiscated from the illegal wildlife trade in Viet Nam.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pantel</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chin</surname> <given-names>SY</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <issue-title>Proceeding of the Workshop on Trade and Conservation of Pangolins Native to South and Southeast Asia.</issue-title> <source>Singapore Zoo, Singapore</source>, <fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>118</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dehnhard</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hildebrandt</surname> <given-names>TB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knauf</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jewgenow</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kolter</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Göritz</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Comparative endocrine investigations in three bear species based on urinary steroid metabolites and volatiles.</article-title> <source>Theriogenology</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>1755</fpage>–<lpage>1761</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.theriogenology.2006.01.012">10.1016/j.theriogenology.2006.01.012</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaubert</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Antunes</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Assessing the taxonomic status of the Palawan pangolin <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Manis</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">culionensis</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> (<tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="order">Pholidota</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>) using discrete morphological characters.</article-title> <source>Journal of Mammalogy</source> <volume>86</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>1068</fpage>–<lpage>1074</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1644/1545-1542(2005)86[1068:ATTSOT]2.0.CO;2">10.1644/1545-1542(2005)86[1068:ATTSOT]2.0.CO;2</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname> <given-names>WY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tao</surname> <given-names>SZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Primary exploration on rearing technique of pangolin.</article-title> <source>Chinese Journal of Zoology</source> <volume>18</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>26</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Heath</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hammel</surname> <given-names>HT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Body temperature and rate of O<sub>2</sub> consumption in Chinese pangolins.</article-title> <source>American Journal of Physiology</source> <volume>250</volume>: <fpage>377</fpage>–<lpage>382</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Heath</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Twenty-four-hour variations in activity, core temperature, metabolic rate, and respiratory quotient in captive Chinese pangolins.</article-title> <source>Zoo Biology</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1002/zoo.1430060102">10.1002/zoo.1430060102</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Heath</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanderlip</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Biology, husbandry, and veterinary care of captive Chinese Pangolins (<italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Manis</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">pentadactyla</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>).</article-title> <source>Zoo Biology</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>293</fpage>–<lpage>312</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1002/zoo.1430070402">10.1002/zoo.1430070402</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Heath</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992a</year>) <article-title><italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Manis</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">pentadactyla</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>.</article-title> <source>Mammalian species</source> (<issue>414</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.2307/3504143">10.2307/3504143</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Heath</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992b</year>) <article-title><italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Manis</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">temminckii</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>.</article-title> <source>Mammalian species</source> (<issue>415</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.2307/3504220">10.2307/3504220</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Heath</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title><italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Manis</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">crassicaudata</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>.</article-title> <source>Mammalian species</source> (<issue>513</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.2307/3504173">10.2307/3504173</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoyt</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Pangolins: past, present, and future.</article-title> <source>AAZPA National Conference Proceedings</source>, <fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>134</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Israel</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sinclair</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grewal</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoefer</surname> <given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <source>Indian wildlife</source>. <publisher-name>APA Productions (HK) Ltd.</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Hong Kong</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>LY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <source>General Zoology</source> (<edition>3rd edition</edition>). <publisher-name>Higher Education Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Beijing</publisher-loc>, <size units="page">533 pp</size>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Pangolin’s habits and its resource protection.</article-title> <source>Chinese Journal of Zoology</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B20">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lumley</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Michalczyk</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitson</surname> <given-names>JJN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spurgin</surname> <given-names>LG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Godwin</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dickinson</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname> <given-names>OY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Emerson</surname> <given-names>BC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chapman</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gage</surname> <given-names>MJG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Sexual selection protects against extinction.</article-title> <source>Nature</source> <volume>522</volume>: <fpage>470</fpage>–<lpage>473</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/nature14419">10.1038/nature14419</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <!--PageBreak-->
      <ref id="B21">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) T<source>he mammalian fauna of Guizhou</source>. <publisher-name>Guizhou Science and Technology Publishing House</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Guiyang</publisher-loc>, <fpage>169</fpage>–<lpage>172</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B22">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Masui</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1967</year>) <article-title>Birth of Chinese pangolin (<italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Manis</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">pentadactyla</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>) at Ueno Zoo, Tokyo.</article-title> <source>International Zoo Yearbook</source> <volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>114</fpage>–<lpage>116</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/j.1748-1090.1967.tb00340.x">10.1111/j.1748-1090.1967.tb00340.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B23">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Menzies</surname> <given-names>JI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1967</year>) <article-title>A preliminary note on the birth and development of a Small-scaled tree pangolin <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Manis</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">tricuspis</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> at Ife University Zoo.</article-title> <source>International Zoo Yearbook</source> <volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <lpage>114</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/j.1748-1090.1967.tb00339.x">10.1111/j.1748-1090.1967.tb00339.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B24">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohapatra</surname> <given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Panda</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Husbandry, Behaviour and Conservation Breeding of India Pangolin.</article-title> <source>Folia Zoologica</source> <volume>63</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>73</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B25">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogilvie</surname> <given-names>PW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bridgwater</surname> <given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1967</year>) <article-title>Notes on the breeding of an Indian pangolin <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Manis</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">crassicaudatu</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> at Oklahoma Zoo.</article-title> <source>International Zoo Yearbook</source> <volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>116</fpage>–<lpage>118</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/j.1748-1090.1967.tb00341.x">10.1111/j.1748-1090.1967.tb00341.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B26">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Panda</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mishra</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohapatra</surname> <given-names>SN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Nandankanan faunal diversity</source>. <publisher-name>Nandankanan Biological Park, Forest and Environment Department</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Government of Odisha</publisher-loc>, <volume>28</volume>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B27">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Prater</surname> <given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>The book of India animals</source>. <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New Delhi</publisher-loc>, <fpage>301</fpage>–<lpage>303</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B28">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname> <given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>YG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>The preliminary study on captive breeding pangolins.</article-title> <source>Forest Science and Technology</source> (<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>28</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B29">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Silk</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Eating for two: Behavioral and environmental correlates of gestation length among free-ranging baboons (<italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Papio</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">cynocephalus</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>).</article-title> <source>International Journal of Primatology</source> <volume>7</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>583</fpage>–<lpage>602</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/BF02736663">10.1007/BF02736663</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B30">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Trivers</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Willard</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1973</year>) <article-title>Natural selection of parental ability to vary the sex ratio of offspring.</article-title> <source>Science</source> <volume>179</volume>: <fpage>90</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1126/science.179.4068.90">10.1126/science.179.4068.90</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B31">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Ee</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1966</year>) <article-title>A note on breeding the cape pangolin <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Manis</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">temminckii</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> at Bloemfontein Zoo.</article-title> <source>International Zoo Yearbook</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>163</fpage>–<lpage>164</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/j.1748-1090.1966.tb01734.x">10.1111/j.1748-1090.1966.tb01734.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B32">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>CY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Behavior observations of the Chinese pangolin under artificial rearing.</article-title> <source>Journal of Economic Animal</source> <volume>4</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B33">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>The gestation length of wild mammals.</article-title> <source>Chinese Journal of Wildlife</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B34">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>QS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <source>The mammal fauna of Anhui</source>. <publisher-name>Anhui Publishing House of Science and Technology</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Hefei</publisher-loc>, <fpage>106</fpage>–<lpage>109</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B35">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Husbandry of pangolins <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Manis</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic> spp.</article-title> <source>International Zoo Yearbook</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>248</fpage>–<lpage>251</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/j.1748-1090.1994.tb03578.x">10.1111/j.1748-1090.1994.tb03578.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B36">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <source>Notes on a newborn Chinese pangolin (<italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Manis</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">pentadactyla</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="subspecies">aurita</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>)</source>. <publisher-name>J Qinghai Normal University (Natural Science)</publisher-name> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B37">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>NF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname> <given-names>GZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>ZR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004a</year>) <article-title>A current situation of ecology study on pangolins.</article-title> <source>Chinese Journal of Zoology</source> <volume>39</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>46</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B38">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004b</year>) <article-title>Assessment of threatened status of Chinese pangolin (<italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Manis</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">pentadactyla</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>).</article-title> <source>Chinese Journal of Applied and Environmental Biology</source> <volume>10</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>456</fpage>–<lpage>461</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B39">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname> <given-names>GZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname> <given-names>QX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname> <given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Studies of conservation biology on Chinese Pangolin (<italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Manis</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">pentadactyla</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>)</source>. <publisher-name>Chinese Forest Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Beijing</publisher-loc>, <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B40">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>CW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname> <given-names>CY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname> <given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Block</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lorentsen</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chin</surname> <given-names>JSC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dierenfeld</surname> <given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>History and dietary husbandry of pangolins in captivity.</article-title> <source>Zoo Biology</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>230</lpage>. doi: <ext-link xlink:type="simple" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1002/zoo.20134">10.1002/zoo.20134</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <!--PageBreak-->
      <ref id="B41">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>CW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>ZW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname> <given-names>XW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname> <given-names>YL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname> <given-names>ZY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>The study of Chinese pangolin in Taiwan. The research report of Taipei Zoo in 2001</source>, <publisher-loc>Taipei</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B42">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Animal reproduction</source> (<edition>2nd edition</edition>). <publisher-name>China Agriculture Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Beijing</publisher-loc>, <fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>198</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B43">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Reproductive of parameters of the Sunda pangolin, <italic><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Manis</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">javanica</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name></italic>.</article-title> <source>Folia Zoologica</source> <volume>64</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>129</fpage>–<lpage>135</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B44">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Giant panda ex-situ conservation theory and practice</source>. <publisher-name>Science Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Beijing</publisher-loc>, <fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>272</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B45">
        <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu-Ge</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <source>Fauna of Zhejiang (<tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="class">Mammalia</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>)</source>. <publisher-name>Zhejiang Science and Technology Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Hangzhou</publisher-loc>, <fpage>60</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>