<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.244.4034</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Description of three new 
                    <italic>Triaenodes</italic> species from Fiji (Trichoptera, Leptoceridae)
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Johanson</surname>
                        <given-names>Kjell Arne</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:F2A38CF6-59EB-4F88-BFEB-761DBEA7B01A</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Eriksson</surname>
                        <given-names>Maertha</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:FF871351-2051-42F5-9C67-7E51E6A1FF20</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Müller</surname>
                        <given-names>Hanna</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:0B49747E-F67E-43E4-A54F-A1BD8F237FA6</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Li</surname>
                        <given-names>Helena Puranen</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:26467FCB-F05C-425E-88C4-2C58180640CC</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Department of Entomology, Swedish Museum of Natural History, Box 50007, SE-104 05 Stockholm, Sweden
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Kjell Arne Johanson (<email xlink:type="simple">kjell.arne.johanson@nrm.se</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: R. Holzenthal</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>19</day>
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>244</issue>
            <fpage>21</fpage>
            <lpage>31</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>25</day>
                    <month>9</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>14</day>
                    <month>11</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Kjell Arne Johanson, Maertha Eriksson, Hanna Müller, Helena Puranen Li</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:88006390-FB9B-4E6F-A97B-8C5877F4EE3B</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>The following three new species are illustrated and described from Fiji: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes rebellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Eriksson &amp; Johanson, <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes oscitus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Müller &amp; Johanson, <bold>sp. n.</bold>, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes forcipatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Puranen Li &amp; Johanson, <bold>sp. n.</bold> All species are endemic to Viti Levu. A key to the male <italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> species of Fiji is provided. With this report, the number of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> species known from Fiji is doubled.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Caddisflies</kwd>
                <kwd>Terrestrial Arthropod Survey of Fiji</kwd>
                <kwd>new species</kwd>
                <kwd>taxonomy</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>In number of species, <tp:taxon-name>Trichoptera</tp:taxon-name> (caddisflies) constitute the second largest monophyletic group of aquatic animals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Malm et al. submitted</xref>). About 13.500 species are described so far, of which about 15% are classified in the family <tp:taxon-name>Leptoceridae</tp:taxon-name> Leach, 1815, which globally is ranked as the 2nd largest family in the order (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Morse 2012</xref>). With 276 described species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Morse 2012</xref>) the leptocerids is the family in the Austral<!--PageBreak-->ian Region comprising the highest species diversity. The species of the family are characteristic in having adults with very long antennae, two rows of setae dorsally on the mesonotum, and narrow forewings. The sistergroup to the <tp:taxon-name>Leptoceridae</tp:taxon-name> is presently not identified, but based on phylogenetic analyses derived from molecular data the family is hypothesized related to <tp:taxon-name>Calamoceratidae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Atriplectidae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Odontoceridae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Philorheithridae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Malm et al. submitted</xref>). In the Australian Region, the <tp:taxon-name>Leptoceridae</tp:taxon-name> are easily distinguished from these families in the absence of preapical tibial spurs on the mid legs, from <tp:taxon-name>Philorheithridae</tp:taxon-name> by the long antennae, from <tp:taxon-name>Philorheithridae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Odontoceridae</tp:taxon-name> by having separate R1 and R2 at the forewing margin, and from <tp:taxon-name>Calamoceratidae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Philorheithridae</tp:taxon-name> by the narrower forewings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Neboiss 1986</xref>). The family comprises two subfamilies <tp:taxon-name>Leptocerinae</tp:taxon-name> Leach, 1815 and <tp:taxon-name>Triplectidinae</tp:taxon-name> Ulmer, 1906. <tp:taxon-name>Triaenodini</tp:taxon-name> is one of 11 tribes within <tp:taxon-name>Leptocerinae</tp:taxon-name>, and comprises the three genera <italic><tp:taxon-name>Adicella</tp:taxon-name></italic> McLachlan, 1877, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Erotesis</tp:taxon-name></italic> McLachlan, 1877 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> McLachlan, 1865 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Malm and Johanson 2011</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> is known from all major faunal biogeographic regions and about 240 extant species have been described so far (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Morse 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Johanson et al. 2011</xref>), and the extinct <italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes fossilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Wichard &amp; Barnard, 2005 dated to Eocene, described from Baltic amber, represents the only fossil species in the genus. With 78 previously recorded species, the diversity is higher in the Australian Region compared to other regions. More than half of these (44 species) were described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Neboiss and Wells (1998)</xref> as endemic to Australia. So far two species are known from Vanuatu (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Johanson et al. 2011</xref>), four from Solomon Islands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Kimmins 1957</xref>), 21 from New Guinea (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Morse 2012</xref>), and three from Fiji. The first record of of the genus from Fiji was given by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Mosely (1934)</xref> who described <italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes dubius</tp:taxon-name></italic> Mosely, 1934 from Wainganitu. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Banks (1936)</xref> described a second species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes manni</tp:taxon-name></italic> Banks, 1936, from Wainganitu. The third species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes fijianus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Mosely, 1941 was described from Viti Levu. This paper adds three more species of the genus from Fiji.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods">
            <title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>The study is based on five males collected in the Terrestrial Arthropod Survey of Fiji project (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Evenhuis and Bickel 2005</xref>) funded by the US National Science Foundation and the Schlinger Foundation. In this project <tp:taxon-name>Trichoptera</tp:taxon-name> were collected in Malaise traps situated at 47 localities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Johanson and Oláh 2012</xref>) on the four major islands Viti Levu, Vanua Levu, Taveuni Island and Kadavu Island between September 21 2002 and January 5 2005. The <italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimens covered in this report were collected from four different localities at Viti Levu Island. The material is stored in 80% alcohol. Right wing pairs of the holotype of all new species and non-types of previously described species were removed, mounted on slides in glycerol and photographed using the Lumenera InfinityX digital camera mounted on an Olympus SZX12 stereomicroscope. The Extended Focus Option in the DeltaPix Insight software was used to create high-resolution photos with high focus depth. The abdomens were cleared in hot 8% KOH for about one hour. The abdomens were dehydrated in absolute alcohol and temporarily mounted<!--PageBreak--> in Euparal on a microscope slide before examination and drawing. All drawings were produced using a pencil on plain white A4 paper sheets using a drawing tube mounted on a Leitz Ortholux II. After the drawings were completed the abdomens were returned to the alcohol vial with the rest of the animal. Each pencil illustration was digitalized in a scanner at low resolution and thereafter used as a background layer in Adobe<sup>©</sup> Photoshop<sup>©</sup> 8.0. The illustrations were completed after being re-drawn on a new layer using a Wacom drawing pad before the background layer was deleted.</p>
            <p>The nomenclature applied to the genitalic morphology follows that of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Malm and Johanson (2011)</xref>. Specimens in this study are deposited in the following repositories:</p>
            <p><bold>FNIC</bold>	Fiji National Insect Collection, Suva, Fiji (currently held at BPBM)</p>
            <p><bold>NHRS</bold>	Swedish Museum of Natural History, Stockholm, Sweden</p>
            <p>The geographical setting of the localities are presented in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Johanson and Oláh (2012)</xref>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Descriptions">
            <title>Descriptions</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Triaenodes</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">rebellus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:CC66BD00-165A-446E-BF77-EC1CAEEECAD9</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Triaenodes_rebellus</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Eriksson &amp; Johanson</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">, 4–8</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes rebellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> resembles the New Guinean species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes mondoanus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kimmins, 1962 by having the dorsal right posterior margin of segment IX strongly produced posteriorly into a needle-shaped process. The new species is easily separated from <italic>mondoanus</italic> by the upper part of tergum X being about as long as the cerci, not much longer than cerci as in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes mondoanus</tp:taxon-name></italic>; and the basomesal process and dorsal branch of each coxopodite is present, while absent in <italic>mondoanus</italic>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description, male.</title>
                    <p>Wings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig 1</xref>). Forewing 5.2 mm, hind wing 4.3 mm (N=1). Forewing: stem of M absent; forks I and V present; wing membrane with pale area along apical margin, mid-anterior margin, and basal two-thirds of posterior margin. Hyaline area present at anastomosis. Hind wing: uniformly gray without apparent patterns.</p>
                    <p>Genitalia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 4–8</xref>). Segment IX wide, asymmetric; in lateral view with ventral part produced posteriorly, anterior margin slightly convex, ventral margin concave; in dorsal view almost rectangular, anterior margin with central part slightly produced anterad; in ventral view broad anterior half and slightly narrower posterior half separated by narrow incision, anterior margin of segment IX deeply concave, lateral margins slightly concave, posterior margin straight. Dorsal right posterior margin of segment IX strongly produced posterad, forming almost straight, needle-shaped process exceeding processes of tergum X (visible in dorsal view and right lateral view), bow-shaped, gently curved mesally. Cerci straight, thin, elongate; covered with long, robust, and short, weak se<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->tae. Tergum X with well-developed upper and lower part, upper part about as long as cerci; forming central, slender, elongate, slightly dorsoventrally flattened process, setose at apical one-third; in lateral view with basal half almost straight, curving ventrally from mid-length (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 4</xref>); in dorsal view slender, hourglass-shaped, with irregular lateral margins at distal one-third. Lower part of tergum X bilobed from base, each lobe thin, strongly elongate, significantly longer than cerci, right lobe slightly shorter than left lobe and tuboid at apex, left lobe slightly club-shaped at apex; in lateral view each lobe curved ventrally; in dorsal view almost parallel. Coxopodites in lateral view, with basal half almost circular, each divided at mid-length into dorsal and ventral branch, posterior margin above dorsal branch undulating. Each dorsal branch about one-third as long as total length of each coxopodite, originating from mid-height of basal part, tube-shaped, with two long apical setae; weakly bent dorsally at mid-length in lateral view; diverging apically in ventral view. Ventral branch of each coxopodite abundantly setose, more densely posteriorly; in lateral view bent dorsad at mid-length, apical part thin; in ventral view widest at base, lateral margin undulating, mesal margin sigmoid, apically diverging. Each basomesal process slender, apically club-shaped with abundant thick spines; in lateral view curved ventrally, reaching as far out as apex of dorsal branch; in ventral view straight or weakly curving mesally. Phallic organ about as long as dorsal part of tergum X; strongly curved ventrally immediately before mid-length, phallobase subtriangular, phallotheca slender immediately after phallobase, uniformly widening apically; endotheca apparently trilobed, membranous, without spines.</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 1–3.</label>
                        <caption><p>Right wings of holotypes. <bold>1</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes rebellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>2</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes oscitus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>3</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes forcipatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-244-021-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 4–8.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes rebellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., holotype. <bold>4</bold> genitalia lateral view <bold>5</bold> genitalia dorsal view <bold>6</bold> genitalia ventral view <bold>7</bold> phallus lateral view <bold>8</bold> phallus ventral view.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-244-021-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p>Holotype male: Fiji: Viti Levu Island, Naitasiri Province, Nakobalevu Mt., rainforest, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">18°03'S, 178°25'E</named-content>, 340 m, Malaise trap, 22.ix–9.x.2002, leg. M. Irwin, E. Schlinger &amp; M. Tokoka’a. [FNIC, alcohol]</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Rebellus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, from Latin <italic>rebellis</italic>, insurgent in English, referring to genitalia being armed by many pointed processes<!--PageBreak-->.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Triaenodes</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">oscitus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:72DEDCDE-DE32-4177-B248-28AA3F894EE0</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Triaenodes_oscitus</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Müller &amp; Johanson</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 2</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">, 9–13</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>The species resembles <italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes rebellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. in the shape of the ventral branch of the coxopodites and basomesal processes, but dorsal branch of each coxopodite is absent. The dorsal appendages of <italic>oscitus</italic> resemble those of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes grifo</tp:taxon-name></italic> Malicky, 2005, but the upper part of tergum X of <italic>oscitus</italic> is longer.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description, male.</title>
                    <p>Wings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 2</xref>). Forewing damaged, hind wing 4.1 mm (N=1).</p>
                    <p>Forewing: stem of M absent; forks I and V present; apex missing in holotype; membrane pale, except in distal one-third with two almost vertical series of dark spots, and a larger dark patch above vertical series. Hyaline area at anastomosis. Basal two-thirds with irregular pale fields. Hind wing: uniformly gray, with faint spots at apical half.</p>
                    <p>Genitalia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 9–13</xref>). Segment IX in lateral view with slightly convex anterior margin, dorsal margin short, continuous with dorsal margin of tergum X; ventral two-thirds strongly produced into posterior lobe; posterior lobe with weakly undulating dorsal margin and nearly straight ventral margin except bending ventrally at apex, posterior margin almost truncate. Large triangular, vertical, posteriorly oriented plate located laterally and at mid-length of segment IX, forming narrow, posteriorly orienting processes. In ventral view anterior margin deeply concave; widest before lateral plates, with slightly concave lateral margins; uniformly narrowing after lateral plates. Posterior margins distinct laterally, mesally apparently fusing with gonopods. Cerci elongate, straight, serrated along their lengths, scattered setose, with row of minute setae along anterior three-quarters of ventral margin; in lateral view oriented almost horizontally, basal one-fifth about two times thicker than distal part; in dorsal view slightly diverging, equally wide along their lengths. Tergum X divided into well-developed upper and lower part. Upper part of tergum X slender, about as long as each cercus; slightly curvilinear ventrally along its length in lateral view; basally wide, slender after one-third its length in dorsal view, apex club-shaped, with short, stout setae. Width of base and apex subequal in lateral view. Lower part of tergum X branching at base into two long, needle-shaped processes, clearly longer than upper part of tergum X, curved ventrally along their lengths, reaching further posteriorly than apex of dorsal part of tergum X; in dorsal view slightly diverging. Gonopods each divided into one-branched coxopodite and basomesal process; about two-fifths as long as each cercus. Coxopodites with scattered setae; each with row of smaller setae along central part of dorsal margin; wide at base in lateral view, stepwise narrowing from about one-third, almost sickle-shaped; apex produced dorsally, nearly tangential with phallus. In ventral view, basal one-quarter of coxopodites separated by longitudinal suture, well-separated from one-quarter, each coxopodite forming dorsoventrally flattened, spoon-shaped plate, with serrated mesal margin; apices of coxopodites diverging. Left coxopodite shorter than right coxopodite, apically blunt. Basomesal processes about two-thirds as long as coxopodites; sickle-shaped in lateral view, each process oriented dorsally at base, <!--PageBreak-->curving posterad and slightly broadening towards apex, bearing strong, lateroventrally and slightly anteriorly directed spines. In ventral view processes running parallel along their lengths; each process with slightly narrowing apex, mesal margin almost straight, lateral margins with small indentations. Phallic organ widest at base and endotheca, narrowest immediately before endotheca; in lateral view with nearly triangular phallobase; phallotheca slender, widening distally and strongly curving ventrally at about mid-length. In dorsal view endotheca forming irregular lobes.</p>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 9–13.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes oscitus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., holotype. <bold>9</bold> genitalia lateral view <bold>10</bold> genitalia dorsal view <bold>11</bold> genitalia ventral view <bold>12</bold> phallus lateral view <bold>13</bold> phallus ventral view.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-244-021-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                    <title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p>The right cercus is broken at mid-length in the holotype.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p>Holotype male: Fiji: Sigatoka Province, Sigatoka Sand Dunes National Park, coastal forest, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">18°10'S, 177°30'E</named-content>, 10 m, Malaise trap, 22.ix–8.x.2002, leg. M. Irwin, E. Schlinger &amp; M. Tokoka’a. [FNIC, alcohol]</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Oscitus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, from Latin <italic>oscito</italic>, gape or open mouth in English, in reference to the shape of the male gonopods in lateral view.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Triaenodes</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">forcipatus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:FECEF693-62B6-4747-B626-531F63F49B43</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Triaenodes_forcipatus</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Puranen Li &amp; Johanson</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 3</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">, 14–18</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>The species is most similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes kalydon</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Malicky, 2005) from Sumatra, particularly in the male genitalia which comprise two-branched coxopodites and absence of the upper part of tergum X. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes forcipatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is easily distinguished from <italic>kalydon</italic> by having much smaller basomesal processes, downward curving gonopods and longer cerci.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description, male.</title>
                    <p>Wings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig 3</xref>). Forewing 5.2–5.9 mm (N=3), hind wing 4.0–4.6 (N=3). Forewing: stem of M absent; forks I and V present; wing membrane with pale area at apex and basal one-third of posterior margin, two rectangular pale fields<!--PageBreak--> at anterior margin, well separated by dark area. Hyaline area present at anastomosis. Hind wing: uniformly gray, without apparent patterns.</p>
                    <p>Genitalia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 14–18</xref>). Segment IX almost triangular in lateral view, ventrally produced posterad before gonopods; ventral margin two times longer than dorsal margin; in dorsal view slightly longer than wide, central part of anterior margin produced anteriorly into rounded lobe; in ventral view anterior margin deeply concave, posterior margin shallowly concave, anterior two-thirds almost two times wider than posterior one-third, sightly pointed laterad at mid-length. Cerci originating from posterodorsal margin of segment IX, uniformly broad along their lengths, with irregular lateral and mesal margins; setose; apex unevenly narrowing; in lateral view posteriorly slightly exceeding gonopods. Tergum X consisting of lower part, upper part vestigial and not evident; lower part separated from near base into lateral branches slightly longer than cerci, forming a pair of posteriorly elongate processes originating immediately below cerci; basally wide in lateral view, strongly narrowing from basal one-sixth, uniformly slender along posterior five-sixths, apex pointed, proximal two-thirds of left branch nearly straight, distal one-third slightly curving ventrally; right branch sigmoid, with posteriorly orienting distal one-third; connected ventrally by concave plate. Gonopods in lateral view as high as posteriormost part of segment IX, <!--PageBreak-->each divided at mid-length into dorsal and ventral branch, dorsal branch about half width of ventral branch, slightly shorter than ventral branch, dorsal branch bearing marginal setae, ventral branch with scattered setae. In ventral view, anterior half of gonopods forming broad plates being completely fused anteriorly, distal half about half as wide as anterior half, slightly curving laterally, two times longer than wide; each with mesal margin sigmoid, apex almost pointed. Basomesal processes as long and wide as ventral branches, originating from anterior one-quarter of gonopods; apex club-shaped with few setae. Phallic organ strongly curving ventrally; in lateral view phallobase slightly elliptic, phallicata widening immediately after phallobase; endotheca rounded; in ventral view distal end of phallotheca about half as wide as proximal end; endotheca rounded, almost triangular, membranous.</p>
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 14–18.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes forcipatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., holotype. <bold>14</bold> genitalia lateral view <bold>15</bold> genitalia dorsal view <bold>16</bold> genitalia ventral view <bold>17</bold> phallus lateral view <bold>18</bold> phallus ventral view.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-244-021-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p>Holotype male: Fiji: Viti Levu Island, Pabitra, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">17.5833°S, 178.0833°E</named-content>, 1034 m, Malaise trap, 17–20.xi.2003, leg. Delena Veikovi, Wabu Baseline Survey [FNIC, alcohol].</p>
                    <p>Paratypes: 5 males: Fiji: Viti Levu Island, Vuda Province, Koroyanitu Natural History Park, Savuione Trail, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">17°40'S, 177°33'E</named-content>, 450 m, Malaise trap, 12–19.x.2002, leg. M. Irwin, E. Schlinger &amp; M. Tokoka’a [NHRS, alcohol].</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymologi">
                    <title>Etymologi.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Forcipatus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, from Latin <italic>forceps</italic>, claw in English, referring to the claw-shaped gonopods in lateral view.</p>
                    <sec sec-type="Key to the Fijian species of Triaenodes, based on characters on male genitalia">
                        <title>Key to the Fijian species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes</tp:taxon-name></italic>, based on characters on male genitalia</title>
                        <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                            <table>
                                <tbody>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cerci in dorsal view about three times longer than wide</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes dubia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Mosely, 1934</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cerci in dorsal view more than four times longer than wide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 4</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">, 9</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">, 14</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Each coxopodite with one branch (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 9</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Each coxopodite with two branches (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 4</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">, 14</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uppermost part of tergum X less than five times longer than wide</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes fijianus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Mosely, 1941</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uppermost part of tergum X more than six times longer than wide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 9, 10</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">In lateral view, ventral branch of coxopodite about as thick as basomesal process (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 9</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes oscitus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Müller &amp; Johansson, sp. n.</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">In lateral view, ventral branch of coxopodite about two times thicker than basomesal process</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes manni</tp:taxon-name></italic> Banks, 1936</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basomesal process curving ventrad in lateral view; dorsal and ventral branches of coxopodite curving dorsad in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 4</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes rebellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Eriksson &amp; Johanson, sp. n.</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basomesal process nearly straight and almost parallel with dorsal and ventral branches of coxopodite in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 14</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Triaenodes fuscipatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Puranen Li &amp; Johanson, sp. n.<!--PageBreak--></td>
                                    </tr>
                                </tbody>
                            </table>
                        </table-wrap>
                    </sec>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>The above material was provided by the Terrestrial Arthropod Survey of Fiji project, funded in part by The National Science Foundation (DEB-0425790) and the Schlinger Foundation. The government of Fiji (Ministries of Environment and Forestry) and the Wildlife Conservation Society, Suva Office, are thanked for their support of the project. KAJ thanks E.I. Schlinger (The World Spider Parasitoid Laboratory, Santa Ynez, CA, USA) and N. Evenhuis (BPBN) for inviting him to analyze the <tp:taxon-name>Trichoptera</tp:taxon-name> collected from the Survey.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Banks</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1936</year>)<article-title> Trichoptera from the Fiji islands.</article-title> <source>Psyche </source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>-<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Evenhuis</surname> <given-names>NL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bickel</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> The NSF-Fiji Terrestrial Arthropod Survey: overview.</article-title> <source>Bishop Museum Occasional Papers </source> <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Johanson</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oláh</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)<article-title> Revision of the Fijian <italic>Chimarra</italic> (Trichoptera, Philopotamidae) with description of 24 new species.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>3354</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>58</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Johanson</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malm</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Espeland</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> The Trichoptera of Vanuatu.</article-title> <source>Deutsche Entomologische Zeitschrift </source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>279</fpage>-<lpage>320</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1002/mmnd.201100031">10.1002/mmnd.201100031</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimmins</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1957</year>)<source> Neuroptera and Trichoptera collected by Mr. J.D. Bradley on Guadalcanal Island, 1953-54. Bulletin of the British Museum (Natural History) Entomology 5: 287–308.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimmins</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1962</year>)<article-title> Miss L. E. Cheesman’s expeditions to New Guinea. Trichoptera.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the British Museum (Natural History) Entomology </source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>97</fpage>-<lpage>187</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Leach</surname> <given-names>WE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1815</year>)<article-title> Entomology.</article-title> <source>Brewster’s Edinburgh Encyclopaedia </source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>52</fpage>-<lpage>172</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Malicky</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<source> Beiträge zur Kenntnis asiatischer <italic>Triaenodes</italic> McLachlan 1865 (Trichoptera, Leptoceridae). Zeitschrift der Arbeitsgemeinschaft Österreichischer Entomologen 57: 33–46.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Malm</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johanson</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<source> A new classification of the long-horned caddisflies (Trichoptera: Leptoceridae) based on molecular data. BMC Evolutionary Biology 11: 10. </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2148-11-10">10.1186/1471-2148-11-10</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Malm</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johanson</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wahlberg</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>submitted</year>) <source>The evolutionary history of Trichoptera: a case of successful adaptation to life in freshwater.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>McLachlan</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1865</year>)<source> Trichoptera Britannica. A monograph of British species of caddis-flies. Transactions of the Entomological Society of London, Series 3, 5: 1–184.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>McLachlan</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1877</year>)<source> A monographic revision and synopsis of the Trichoptera of the European fauna. Part 6, John van Voorst, London, pp. 281–348, plates 32–37.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Morse</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>  <role>(Ed)</role> (<year>2012</year>)<source> Trichoptera World Checklist. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://entweb.clemson.edu/database/trichopt/index.htm">http://entweb.clemson.edu/database/trichopt/index.htm</ext-link>  [accessed 20 January 2012]</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mosely</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1934</year>)<article-title> New Fijian and African Trichoptera.</article-title> <source>Eos </source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>-<lpage>27</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mosely</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1941</year>)<article-title> Fijian Trichoptera in the British Museum.</article-title> <source>Annals and Magazine of Natural History </source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>361</fpage>-<lpage>373</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Neboiss</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>)<source> Atlas of Trichoptera of the SW Pacific-Australian Region, Series Entomologica 37. Dr W. Junk, Dordrecht.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Neboiss</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<article-title> Review of Australian species of <italic>Triaenodes</italic> McLachlan (Trichoptera: Leptoceridae).</article-title> <source>Memoirs of the Museum of Victoria </source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>89</fpage>-<lpage>132</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-94-009-4814-3">10.1007/978-94-009-4814-3</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ulmer</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1906</year>)<source> Neuer beitrag zur kenntnis aussereuropäischer Trichopteren. Notes from the Leyden Museum 28: 1116.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wichard</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnard</surname> <given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Köcherfliegen im Baltischen Bernstein - 5. Nachweis der Gattung <italic>Triaenodes</italic> (Trichoptera: Leptoceridae).</article-title> <source>Mitteilungen aus dem Geologisch-Paläontologischen Institut der Universität Hamburg </source> <volume>89</volume>: <fpage>149</fpage>-<lpage>157</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>